<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of Ware and Sherley as it was set forth in matter of fact and argued in several points of law in the consistory of Dublin, in Michaelmas term 1668. By Dudley Loftus, J.U.D.</title>
            <author>Loftus, Dudley, 1619-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2820</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218143</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829762</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829762</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34205</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34205)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2009:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of Ware and Sherley as it was set forth in matter of fact and argued in several points of law in the consistory of Dublin, in Michaelmas term 1668. By Dudley Loftus, J.U.D.</title>
                  <author>Loftus, Dudley, 1619-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [3], 37-93, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Benjamin Tooke, printer to the Kings most Excellent Majesty, and are to be sold by Samuel Dancer, in Castle-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The case of Mary Ware, and Iames Shirly; as it was argued," has seperate title page on pg. 35.</note>
                  <note>Quire A contains an extra leaf.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: signature D4 lacking; signature D3 has catchword "WE".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Lambeth Palace Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Courts --  Law and legislation --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Criminal justice, Administration of --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:34205:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE CASE OF WARE and SHERLEY As it was ſet forth in matter of FACT And argued in ſeveral points of LAW in the Conſiſtory of <hi>Dublin,</hi> in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term 1668.</p>
                  <p>BY <hi>Dudley Loftus,</hi> J. U. D.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>blin,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, and are to be ſold by <hi>Samuel Dancer,</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet,</hi> 1669.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:34205:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34205:2"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE have with a moſt ſtrict regard obſerued all requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits, even to the leaſt Circumſtance of our duty, in proſecuting the Contumacy of the Defendent in this Cauſe, ſo fair, as right practice, and the known rules of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in this Court, hath inſtructed us, inſomuch that you have upon our humble motion pronounced him Contumacious in not appearing upon due <hi>Preconization ad informandum,</hi> and in <hi>panam Contumaciae,</hi> you have decreed a procedure to the act of information <hi>Contumacia ejus non obſtante,</hi> for my part, I wiſh he were preſent <hi>in juditio,</hi> that I might repreſent unto his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netential thoughts an Hiſtcricall view of his great iniquities and thence leſs injuries my Client hath received from him thereby to bring him to a true ſence of his ſins and his duty in Confeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his delicts, which indeed are ſuch that if he were preſent, none but a <hi>Tertullus</hi> who Cares not how bad the Cauſe be ſo the fee be good, would preſume to ſpeake in his behalf, for were he ſtrengthned with the patronage of the beſt Advocates in the World, and aſſiſted with all other advantages which uſually make Victory hopefull, nothing could be ſaid in his excuſe, yet thus much he may be aſſured of, that though he be Contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly abſent, he ſhall not be overcome by a <hi>Sopracargo</hi> or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34205:3"/>any advantage of proſecution, hitherto, or hereafter to be taken againſt him, unleſs it be, by the burthen of his own Crimes, nor ſhall I take the freedome of ſaying any more in the ſtateing of this Cauſe then I would freely utter were he preſent; for my repreſentation of things of this Nature ſhall never be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportioned like the Evening Shadows, longer then the juſt dimenſions of Truth, which I have alwaies eſteemed as the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks</hi> of the Miſſall, whereunto as the <hi>Ritualiſts</hi> obſerue, it is more dangerous to add then to omit any part thereof, nor ſhall I deſcribe it in the imagery of an Oratour, for it is our advantage to ſet it before you and this Congregation in the plainneſs of a clear and naked repreſentation. I ſhall therefore deceive the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of thoſe who think I am come to this place to ſuborn Common attention with bravery of expreſſions, or to tickle the Eares of the learned, with refined ſubtilties of Law and Scholaſtick diſcourſes my chiefeſt aim being rather to ſatisfie the bench in a ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt Diſcourſe, then the Curioſity of the ſtanders-by in an unneceſſary profuſion of words, for I am of the <hi>Arabian</hi> Authors Mindes who: ſaith there is no benefit <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c. <hi>Viz:</hi> that cauſe may be ſuſpected to want the patronage of Arguments which is pleaded for, only with multiplicity of words, St: <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> makes his entrance into one of his Sermon's with this preparation to attention, <hi>Attendite diligenter non enim rem Vulgarem vobis pollicemur,</hi> I ſhall upon the like ingagement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the heedful attention of every one who is within the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of hearing me this day, for I promiſe you <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> not any thing that falls within the ordinary <hi>Occurrences</hi> of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, but things ſo horrid and dreadful to human eares, that I have not any exaggeration of words great enough to expreſs their <hi>Exorbitancie,</hi> things ſeldom read of in <hi>Pagan</hi> antiquity, but ſo extraordinary and beyond nature prodigious, that they're ſufficient to aſtoniſh Heathens, and make the moſt Barbarous Nations even the wild <hi>Iriſh</hi> and the <hi>Clangregores</hi> in Scotland to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34205:3"/>bluſh; things ſo ſtrange that the baſhful modeſty of an Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſtyle cannot reach unto, nay ſo far above the expreſſions of the boldeſt Poets that there is not ſufficient efficacy in all the words that ever the world made uſe off, from the firſt inſtant of its exiſtancy to this moment of its decrepit Age, to expreſs the nature of them, and ſhould we outlive the period and obſequies of time I am ſure we ſhould never hear of greater <hi>Barbariſmes,</hi> amongſt which there is one of greateſt remarque, a crime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reſt ſo heinouſly flagitious, that the very name there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, carries to every mans underſtanding ſuch a notion of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as it requires as much faith in the Hearers to believe it, as it did wickedneſs in the offenders who perpetrated it, the relation wherof may perhaps wring Teares out of thoſe pale fac't and obdurat walls, put the Bench into a Swett, make the Barr to groan, binde up the ſenſes of the ſtanders-by in the <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity</hi> of a dull amazement, and tranſport my ſelf to the utmoſt bounds of a ſober paſſion whilſt I in the recitall finde an unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomd horror, entring into the Marrow of my ſhivering Bones, &amp; unuſual reſentments invadeing every part of my ſoule. I ſhall ſay no more in General to excite your attention, but betake my ſelfe to the <hi>narratio facti,</hi> wherein I am to ſet forth not onely the fraud and violence which the Defendent uſed againſt the Plaintiff in a moſt <hi>Prodigious rape,</hi> but alſo the impudence of his <hi>Calumny</hi> in the <hi>jactitation</hi> of <hi>Marriage</hi> with hir which I ſhal make good by proofs amounting to a pitch of evidence abovel all poſſibility of Contradiction, and then we ſhall deſire the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage which the Law affords in that caſe, as well by the Courts declaring that there was no <hi>Marriage</hi> lawfully Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted between them, as by inflicting on him the juſt ſeverity of the Law, for his Correction &amp; reformation, and our due repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Before I enter into a recitall of the Cauſe I hope I ſhall not be reckoned amongſt the <hi>Perditempi</hi> if by way of introduction I open a proſpect into the <hi>Contingentia facti,</hi> briefly glancing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34205:4"/>on the perſons for the Diſparity of their Condition will be of force not onely to ſhew the improbability of her conſent to Marry with him, but alſo if the ſaying of <hi>Ariminenſis</hi> be true (<hi>viz:</hi> that) <hi>ex vilitate perſonae offendentis creſcit gravitas injuriae</hi> will much aggravat the rape and the Contumely of his moſt impudent jactitation, of Marriage with her, which like word gives a deeper Colour to his offence and makes it above all reſpects inexcuſable: for of all the reproaches that Satan the old <hi>Calumniator</hi> Could rake out of the fouleſt Channels of Hell, none could be greater or ſharper in her eſteem, and therefore the <hi>Lacedemonian,</hi> who in Commending his Sword ſaid it was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſharper then <hi>Calumny,</hi> if he had ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented ſo ſharp a <hi>Calumny</hi> as this would not have made that Compariſon. Whilſt I ſpeak of the Defendent, I ſhall endeavour to Imitate <hi>Johannes Mylaeus</hi> a famous Iuriſconſult of whom it was ſaid, <hi>ita veritatem amplectebatur, ut dicendi acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitatem vitaret;</hi> As for his fortune, I ſhall ſay nothing, for I am none of thoſe who meaſure the Sutableneſs of Matches by the rate of the ſubſidie books, nor do I think that my Client in the choyſe of a Husband will tye her ſelf ſo ſtrictly to the rule of Logick as to hold that <hi>â quantitate res dicuntur pares aut impares,</hi> we ſhall therfore allow his Patrimony better then his Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or birth, which as reports informe us is very Inconſiderable and far beneath her Extraction, he being a man lately drawn out of the Lees of Poverty, and the obſcurity of a mean Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but of his Original I ſhall ſay nothing nor ſhall I urge any more in the repreſentation of him at preſent then what appears out of the evidences taken in this Cauſe, which denote him to be in his Nature not onely as an impoſtume ready to burſt with a tumid <hi>Plethorie</hi> of ſelf Conceipt, but as a Monſter poſſeſt with a Legion of exceſſive hopes for <hi>ſpes alit agricolas,</hi> and a <hi>Gluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous</hi> deſire to raiſe himſelf to an Eſtate, in proſecution whereof, his ambition Ridd on without Reyns of reſtreynt, until at laſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34205:4"/>
                     <hi>per fas aut ne fas,</hi> he became Maſter of ſome Acres of Land, but then the Tranſportations of ſo unexpected a proſperity, carried him ſo far above himſelf, that he ſcorn'd to ſubject his Appetite to the Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ak of reaſon, or to confine himſelfe within the bounds of Moderation, for <hi>ruſtica gens neſcit habere modum,</hi> he then knows not how to meaſure the height of his Fortune; but by a <hi>Precipice,</hi> and ſo becomes the Ingeneer of his own Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, as being neither wiſe in the Choyce of his purpoſes, not prudent in the uſe of means, nor happy in the imployment of Inſtruments he ſetts on work for the Acchievment of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes. In his Converſation he hath ſhewed himſelf ſo frentleſs a a plece of Impudence that ſhamerfaceneſs never caſt her Vaile on his Fore-head; And ſo little remorſe of Conſcience poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth his Soule that no ſinn ſeems to trouble him which he can Vaile or Maſke from human perception. And ſuch hath been the lowneſs of his minde that the hope of Intereſt did prevaile more with him then the horrour of perpetual Infamy; For he cared not how great miſchiefs he attempted, nor with how much diſgrace, So that his Indirect ends might be attained. Furthermore in his Converſation, he was of ſo moroſe an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, as that he deemed all Civil Complyance with other mens humours, a crooked deformity from his own, He was often ſubject to wrathful diſcompoſures of minde and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hurried by the giddy and rapid Violence of his paſſions to ſuch a paſs; as that he could neither ſpeake ſence nor harken unto reaſon; Whilſt he Evapourated the heat of his inflamed Bowels, he was of ſo obdurat an heart that you might as ſoon Pump water out of the hardeſt Rocks or diſſolue them into ſtreaming Fountains, as draw a Teare of Compaſſion or ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from him, for he eſteemed the bittereſt Tears of oppreſſed Women but as the fluid dropps of a ſickly rheum; Again ſuch was his diſpoſition that he was apt out of ſtomachfull hatred and revenge to Vomit out ſpightfull untruths, and to brand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34205:5"/>his Neighbours with Calumnious Impreſſions; In his amours he was ſodeſtitute of reaſon and ſo much drowned in Senſuality that force and rigour were the onely Arguments he uſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite Conſent, ſeeking ratherby the inſolency of a rude Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and peremptory menaces to Vex Women to a Complyance then by ſoft perſwaſions or the Courtſhip of faire Language civilly to allure them, and when Luſt Commanded the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his Libidinous Limbs, he had no regard to Maidencha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity. I know that <hi>Praeſcientia non ligat res in eventum;</hi> Yet if it were Convenient by a Judicial prognoſtication to foretell the tendency and ſucceſs of affaires, I might perhaps tell him that his Horoſcope hath caſt ſo Ghaſtly a Glance upon his <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity</hi> as doth portend a direfull event, &amp; would if publiſht to his notice like the Fumes of Mercury and Orpiment looſen his joynts to tremblings and diſtortions, and make him in your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion like the <hi>Materia prima</hi> which as <hi>Aquinas</hi> I. <hi>Par. q.</hi> 5. <hi>Art.</hi> 3. <hi>ob.</hi> 3. Saith <hi>non habet rationem appetibilis ſed appetentis tantum,</hi> what I have ſaid Concerning the Defendent is rather croſs to my Natural Inclination then a digreſſion: for to ſpeake to any mans prejudice agrees noe otherwiſe with me then as Motion to light or heavie Bodies <hi>Quibus non Competit moveri niſi ſecundum quod ſunt extra diſpoſitionem naturae. Aquin: p:</hi> 1: <hi>q:</hi> 18. but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of my ſubject hath directly led me thereunto, and I finding ſo great a Concours of people tooke the advantage of ſo many Witneſſes to ſhew you how little probability there is, that any Woman ſhould Conſent to marry with a man ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly qualified, eſpecially my Clyent, whom I am now to repreſent unto you, as ſhe is, and therefore, ſo different from his Nature and qualifications, that you will eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that it were as likely to bring two paralel Lines together as to conjoyne theſe two in Marriage, for every one knows that a Judicious woman may be reſembled to our ſence which as St. Thomas obſerues <hi>delectatur rebus debite Proportionatis</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34205:5"/>that it is in Marriage as it is in Muſick <hi>Quo voces ſunt propinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores ſibi invicem, eó meliorem Conflant ſymphoniam</hi> for which reaſon it is ſaid that the <hi>Jonick</hi> and <hi>Hyper Jonick moods</hi> agree better in Muſick, then the <hi>Jonick</hi> and <hi>Dorick,</hi> which agrees with <hi>juſtitia Condecentiae</hi> mentioned in the School-men which tunes up the hearts of Married people to a Melodious uniſone; I am now to draw the other line of the paralel in a true repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of my Client, whereby it will appear the diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between them is too great to be reduced to an adjuſtment and that ſhe could not without renounceing the Honour of her Birth, and putriſiing the memory of her Aunceſtors, level her Affections to the meanneſs of his diſpiſed bed, which cannot be made <hi>Jſoperimetricall</hi> to hir quality, and that they were no more likely to agree in a maritall State, then Contraries can be Lodged together in their moſt intent degrees; nor more likely to be Conjoyn'd in affections then the <hi>literae Illegabiles</hi> in the <hi>Perſian</hi> writings. To ſpeake of her Birth and with my words to Magnifie her in remembrance of the many Vertues and honours which have ſhined with great Brightneſs as well in her Mothers as in her Fathers family would be to no more pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe then to ſhew light to the Sunn, or to breath on a perfect Diamond, and to ſpeake of her fortune would be to publiſh that, which is already well known; Therefore I ſhall tranſ-fer my ſelf from that Conſideration of diſſimilitude between them, unto her Education and Perſonal endowments, She had her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation altogether under her Mother who was not onely a great pattern of Vertue and Modeſty, but a ſevere inſtructer of her in the rudiments of Religion the rules of Morality and all principles of Vertue and Honour, under whoſe Diſciplin ſhe was kept in as ſtrict a regularity as if ſhe had been a <hi>Carmelite</hi> or a <hi>Carthuſian,</hi> as is well known to many who hear me: inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that from her infancy ſhe was ſo brought up, as to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem chaſtity the Richeſt Jewel of the Femal Sex, wherefore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34205:6"/>ſhe hath been ſo well fixt by Education in the center of a Chaſt reſolution, that ſhe could never be drawn (by perſwaſions or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moral inducements of delight co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity or advancement that the World could ſuggeſt unto her) to Yeild to the bent of any exorbitant Luſt or Immodeſt deſire, and ſince the death of her Good Mother, ſhe hath alwaies profeſt that ſhe never thought her will could be carried in its proper Orb, but when it was placed in the good likeing of her neareſt Relations and diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Friends, according to whoſe precepts and Admonitions ſhe endeavoured ſtrictly to conforme her deportment in all things, ſhe is not therefore like the young Women of St. <hi>Frianos</hi> Gate in <hi>Florence,</hi> nor was ſhe when the Defendent unhappily knew her, like the practiceing Dames of <hi>Paris,</hi> who find nothing new or ſtrange the firſt night of their Marriage, nor was ſhe any of thoſe pretenders onely to Chaſtity, who have ſold their Virginities as often as new made Prieſts do their firſt Maſs, but I may ſay in a very high degree of well grounded confidence, that notwithſtanding her late misfortune ſhe is not only an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved example but alſo a wonder of Chaſtity; The like whereof will not perhaps be left upon the Records of this Age (all circumſtances concurring) to the view of Poſterity, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſhe may be perfectly reſembled to the pretty Ermin which had rather expoſe its ſelfe to the hazard of Death by the Hunters Violence, then ſeeke the preſervation of life in the wayes of defilement; So much of her Education in Vertue and modeſty, which gives her a large claime to the knowledge of a worthy deportment: And now I am to ſlide into the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of ſome of her moſt remarkable qualifications which I ſhall briefly ſet forth in the light of Truth but not in the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of Eloquence. In the firſt place ſhe having been inſtructed that an Eſtate without Vertue and merit is but a Teſtimony of good Fortune and no Advancement to felicity, ſhe hath not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavoured to keep her ſelf by a Modeſt retirement out of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34205:6"/>the bad Cuſtoms which over whelm'd this Age, but alſo hath Labour'd the exornation of her ſelf, with all qualities belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Gentlewoman; So that to ſpeak Negatively of her <hi>per remotionem imperfectionis,</hi> ſhe is not blinded with paſſion nor puft up with Pride, nor precipitated by ambition, nor tickled by vaine glory, nor melted by pleaſures, nor inflamed by Luſts, nor inraged with revenge, nor turmoyl'd by Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; And again to deſcribe her poſitively, for the comlineſs of her Statute, Figure, Port, Gate, Complexion, Countenance, Promptneſs of wat, and a fluent Tongue the ready and clear inte peter of her ingenuous conceptions, there are few of her Age who go beyond her; I am reſolved againſt inlargements of diſcourſe otherwiſe I might ſpeak diffuſively of all theſe her laudable indowments, as alſo of her affability which is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of affection, of her courtly accompliſhments conſiſting in a proportionable agreeableneſs and compliance with all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable or tollerable diſpoſitions; If any ſhall object that the above recited qualities are baits which float upon the water without a hook and do rarely catch Husbands, to this I reply that ſhe hath in ſurpluſage of theſe a noble Eſtate ſufficient to recommend her to the prime or at leaſt the ſecond rate of Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands in the Kingdom: and therefore putting all together, I leave it to conſideration whether a Lady ſo highly qualified and advanced above the Defendent in all reſpects, could comport in Marriage with a man of ſo mean an Eſtate and ſo contrary diſpoſitions and habits of mind, in the mean time, I reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that if he had been crown'd with the Royal ſtate and imperial command of all the Kingdoms upon Earth in their moſt Flouriſhing condition and pacifique poſſeſſion, and if ſhe by Marrying him might have enjoyed that univerſal Dominion the length of the worlds duration ſhe would never have conſented to the Fetters of his imbraces.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34205:7"/>
                  <p>I am now nearer approaching to the thing in hand, and am in the firſt place to reduce into a ſuccinct and Methodicall <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative</hi> the beginning progreſs &amp; concluſion of the whole matter of Fact, as well for the information of the Court; as to ſatisfie the curious inquiſition of the People ſo far at leaſt as it is conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to ſtamp a figure of ſo foul a fact in their imagination; for, as it was wiſdom in <hi>Galen</hi> not to leave behind him too ſubtile a Theory of Poyſon, leaſt he ſhould thereby give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for the too ready practice thereof, So I dare not be too particular in relating the many ſubtilties and contrivances which the Defendent uſed in this affair, leaſt bad inclinations in others may be too fully inſtructed to act the like evills, If I ſhould afford them too broad an inſpection extended to all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> And my firſt riſe is, that the Defendent forgetting the aforementioned diſparity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and my Client grew up to ſo high a conceit of himſelf, as that he preſumed to make adreſſes to her in the way of Marriage, which he ſeem'd to proſecute with very much inſtance and ſolicitation: but my Client, though ſhe was young, and not arbitreſs of her condition, yet knowing how to make a juſt eſtimat of her ſelf, and finding nothing in him that might fit him for her acceptance, ſhe immediatly deſired him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge his mind of ſuch vain hopes, and afterwards he renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his motion to the ſame purpoſe, ſhe repel'd him with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and contempt; not out of a feigned unwillingneſs, but a real averſion, and never after looked upon him but with a careleſs diſdain loathing and deteſtation, and withall aſſureing him that it was as eaſie to blow Flint into flames with a paire of Bellows, as to kindle any flames of love in her by the breath of his ſolicitations, for his faireſt words were as harſh to her ears as the noyſe of Pea-cocks, and ſhe took no more delight to ſee him, then ſore eyes do to behold the Sun in its <hi>Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal</hi> altitude, ſhe hated him as a Jew doth Images, or a non-Conformiſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34205:7"/>a Surplice, ſhe feared him as a Monſter and avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him as the Plague; Accounting his company as peſtilenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al as the infectious exhalations of the Dogs ſtar, or the <hi>Maligne influence</hi> of a Comet: And indeed it many times happens that men advanced above deſert from a low degree are like thoſe Exhalations which being raiſed from Dung-hills become Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets of a direfull influence: hereupon the Defendent finding that the more he reinforced his attempts the more ſhe ſtiffned the bent of her reſolution againſt him; inſomuch that her ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt anſwers were ſo far from giving him hopes, that they did exceedingly increaſe his diſpaire, and that there did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in her diſpoſition the leaſt complyant ſoftneſs which might be wrought to his deſire, And that nothing was to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from her but what an inexorable neceſſity could extort, and he being rigidly reſolved to uſe arguments of force, where force of his arguments would not prevail, he ſharpned his revenge as a <hi>Perſian Author</hi> ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> on the Whetſtone of his petrified heart, and put himſelf upon a deſign as Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and <hi>haynouſly flagitious</hi> as the malice of a diſappointed Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition could invent, or the greateſt cruelty perpetrate; And that executed in ſuch manner as never any man who had his face waſh'd at a Chriſtian Font, eſpecially a Proteſtant did own. I ſee ye begin to wonder at what I ſay, but that your thoughts may be the leſs tranſported into admiration, ye may be pleaſed to remember what <hi>Salvianus</hi> hath ſaid <hi>viz.</hi> That ſome in his time were Chriſtians only in <hi>opprobrium &amp; Contumeliam Chriſtianorum,</hi> in ſuch ſence the Defendent may perhaps pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs himſelf a Proteſtant, but to proceed I muſt tell you how he advanced from deſign to endeavour, and from endeavour to act the greateſt violation and injury upon my Client, that ſhe was capable of receiving, (for the greateſt torments that Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants have invented, or Martyrs ſuffer'd, are not to be compared with the <hi>Violation</hi> of <hi>Virginity</hi>) firſt of all therefore by a ſlye and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34205:8"/>crafty inſinuation, he winds himſelf into a familiar, though ſeeret Acquaintance with her Maid whom then ſhe took to be a plain faithful and obſequious ſervant, but afterwards in the event, proved a <hi>ci, ce, Medea,</hi> a <hi>Sphinx,</hi> a meer ſhop of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties, a practized <hi>Medianera</hi> or inſtrument in abomination: he proceeds ſo far as to Bribe this Maids good will to the favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his luſt in the betraying of her Miſtriſs, and draws her ſo far along with him, as that ſhe had at length not only a fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in his Plott, but was alſo ingaged therein up to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes; and with as much endeavour as ſecrecy, induſtriouſly ſerved his deſign, which was then as much hidden from the Plaintiffs obſervation, as is the middle of a right line from our ſight when the raye of Viſion falls upon the Extenſion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the diffinition of a right line thus given in the <hi>Perſian</hi> Language by <hi>Machmad Shah Cholgi</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and after they had a long time wrought in the Vaults of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they contrive by a fraudulent abduction to deliver her to the diſpoſal of his force and Violence, the Maid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pretends an importunat invitation from her ſiſter to ſupp at her houſe in <hi>New-ſtreet,</hi> as a Skreen to the private deſign of her abduction: my Client was at firſt very backward in her Inclination to go thither, yet at length through much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion ſhe condiſcended to that, which, ſo great an importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity had urged her to, and promiſed to go; Whereupon a Coach was prepared, and thither ſhe went, where without the leaſt ſhadow of ſuſpition, ſhe was entertain'd untill about eight of the clock at night, and then as well out of her own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, as out of a deſire to conform to her Parents will, who could not endure her being out late, ſhe was deſirous to repair homewards &amp; betakes her ſelf to her Coach, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put into motion (as ſhe thought homeward) ſhe fell occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally into earneſtneſs of diſcourſe with her Maid, which to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34205:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>with the darkneſs of the night ſo ſurpriſed her animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency of the way, that ſhe never doubted whether ſhe was going, untill at laſt, hearing ſome noyſe ſhe put her head out of the Coach, and then though the night was mantled in much darkneſs, ſhe diſcovered that ſhe was carried beyond Lt. Coll. <hi>Fernlyes</hi> houſe in St. <hi>Cavans-ſtreet,</hi> &amp; there beſett with an armed Troop or Squadren of Horſe conſiſting of about eight Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who ſeemed to be as void of reaſon as they were predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall of words, which together with their rude compulſion uſed in hurrying on the Coach-man intimating their intent on to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry her away by force beſides this ſhe obſerved then in the Carriage of her Maid more then ordinary cauſe to ſuſpect her fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity, and moreover the appearance of the Defendent who at the ſame time flaſh't terrour out of the angry <hi>Caverns</hi> of his Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mified face, caſt the greateſt injections of horrour into her terrified fancy: hereupon cold fear ſeized the blood in her veins, and hudled together her thoughts and ſpirits in ſuch a confuſed amazement, as that ſhe loſt the ſuccours of her uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al reaſon, and knew not well what reſolution to take, then thinking it too Inſignificant an utterance of her grief, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it only in the common evidence of tears or to ſigh out the ſence thereof with a moderate, Woe is me! ſhe according to the ſharpneſs of her <hi>Reſentments</hi> cryed out with the utmoſt extent of a roaring exclamation, imploring aid and pity, but they who would not hear her with patience, nor anſwer her with reſpect, like the bloody ſacrificers of their Children to <hi>Molech</hi> in the fire, drowned her lamentations with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſhouts and moſt obſtreperous noyſes they could make, leaſt her complaints being underſtood, ſhe ſhould be reſcued. I leave you therefore to imagin what ſtrange impreſſions were now begotten in this weak and timorous young Woman, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with the dreadful face of a preſent confuſion, and the fore imagin'd forms of futurein creaſing troubles, whileſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34205:9"/>they with their <hi>Menacing</hi> incitations adding ſpeed unto the Coach-mans pace, every ſtep of her rapid progreſs repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed new horrours to her imagination, inſomuch that ſhe being now carried beyond hope of ſuccour from the Town, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of all aſſiſtance that could Miniſter defence or reſcue unto her in the Countrey; And there being then, no hope of eſcape to any Sanctuary, ſhe being guarded as ſtrictly by theſe Ruffians as was the Holy Sepulcher by the Phariſies: She was tranſported out of her ſenſes into a deep ſoon, but ſhortly after returning out of that Extaſie, ſhe <hi>Meditated</hi> deeply with her new recollected ſenſes, which adviſed her to fortifie her fainting reſolution, and rather to make uſe of the force of reaſon then the <hi>Vehemency</hi> of paſſion; and thereupon ſhe chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her angry and loud Exclamations, into ſoft &amp; mild perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, hopeing thereby to alter the by as of their rigid Inclinations into a Compaſſionat ſence of her ſufferings, and certainly had not their conſciences been ſeared with the hotteſt Iron in the Devils forge they would have been toucht with a ſence of her grief, which would have wrung tears out of a <hi>Marble ſtatute,</hi> but alas her ſoftneſs of ſpeech ſerved but as a burning Glaſs to inflame the paſſions of ſome of them and the ſoftneſs of her words where they moſt prevail'd, were applyed as water caſt upon a Smiths forge, which makes it burn inward with more intenſion for a time, but afterwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s break out with a greater eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amation, ſhe then found the <hi>Arabian</hi> ſaying true which ſounds thus <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Viz.</hi> Where power is wanting endeavour is vain ſhe therefore remains groaning under the deplorable increaſe of her miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries whilſt they in a rude and unmercifull courage, force the Coach-man to incite his Horſes to a ſwiftter courſe; by this time darkneſs had muffled up the face of the world in a hood of obſcurity as dark as Pitch, ſhe being then only hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in not being able to diſcern the Defendent, but much more unhappy in wanting light how to avoid him, ſhe then attempts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34205:9"/>the throwing of her ſelf twice or thrice out of the Coach, either to end her grief with her life, or to eſcape by the obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the night, but ſtill ſhe was prevented by the ſtrictneſs of the guard they held over her, wherefore being now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to obey the overruling force of a violent and invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble neceſſity, ſhe muſt ſit ſtill in the Coach melting her thoughts into the bitter Juice of tears, as if ſhe had bin of the <hi>Hyades</hi> who wept themſelves to death, and as every ſtep of her rapid courſe was a variation of her miſery, ſo ſometimes ſhe implores pity from them, and ſometimes ſhe cryes aloud for help from the Countrey, untill at laſt in the ſwift courſe of ſo great a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſhe was drawn beyound the conduct of her own inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo farr almoſt as the Bridg of <hi>Donogh-brook,</hi> where they forc't her out of the Coach with intent to put her behind one of the Horſe-men, but then, ſhe being tranſported beyond her ordinary temper by ſo juſt a cauſe of Indignation, and being prepared to run through all accidents of fortune, and deſirous rather to precipitat her ſelf into a nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er and more certain danger of death in reſiſtance, then to be carried away further into their mercileſs power, ſhe managed that reliques of her remaining ſtrength to the utmoſt of reſiſtance, and though winter had then caſt its cold influence in great extremity on the earth, ſhe caſt her ſelf into the deep and miery High-way where ſhe remain'd ſo long kneeling in the myre as if her knees had bin rooted in that poſture, and ſtrugled with them in that place, even to the <hi>Laceration</hi> and tearing of her Cloathes and the loſs of ſuch Ornaments as ſhe carried about her, all which time ſhe did with a loud and ſhrill voice repreſent unto the affirighted Neighbours the ſad accents of her oppreſſed heart, expreſſing its ſelf in ſighs groans and moſt lamentable out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries, proclaiming her proteſtations to the world againſt her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along with them, or ever to conſent to marry the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, <hi>ſed ſola erat in agro, Clamavit, &amp; nullus affuit qui liberaret
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34205:10"/>eam,</hi> at length they perſwaded her to a belief of that which they confirm'd with many oaths, which was their promiſe to bring her immediatly to <hi>Dublin</hi> in caſe ſhe would afterwards permit the Defendent to addreſs himſelf unto her, and ſhe being then tyred even to the loſs of breath and unable to make any further conſiderable reſiſtance, told them that on the terms offered, ſhe would admit of his addreſſes in <hi>Dublin,</hi> whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe was put behind one of the Horſemen, but as ſoon as ſhe was mounted on horſeback ſhe found cleerly that all promiſes though confirm'd by oath ſtood for Cyphers in their accompts, for ſhe was immediatly tyed with <hi>Tenacious</hi> knots of ſtrong li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments to one of the moſt Churliſh and moſt Robuſtious Horſemen amongſt them, who with the reſt of that Rude Company, carried her away all that night, when according to their irregular revolutions, of their ſundry paſſions, and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of her interchangeable misfortunes, ſometimes a diſturb'd imagination ſtopt the paſſages of her ſpeech, and ſometimes new and ſharp reſentments gave her a voice to cry out, at length that no parcel of Calamity might be wanting to increaſe her miſery, they declining the high-ways as Heralds do in <hi>Italy,</hi> bring her through the ſolitudes of a Countrey ſo ruinous and deſolate, ſo void of incloſures and habitations and ſo unfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented that the high-ways were not diſtinguiſhable from the reſt of the land, not improperly reſembling the <hi>Arabian</hi> deſerts, where the <hi>Caravan</hi> Pilgrims from <hi>Damaſcus</hi> to <hi>Mecca</hi> find out their way by the compaſs and Starrs: at laſt when ſhe might have grown into ſome doubt of the School-mens doctrine, <hi>de nemine deſperandum in via,</hi> almoſt ſtarved with hunger and cold, ſhe arrived at a Cottage about twenty miles from the City, where being taken from her horſe, a moſt every limb of her as it were complying with the unwillingneſs of her mind, wanted ſence and motion to carry her into the houſe, ſo that they rather out of neceſſity then an officious civility carried
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34205:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>her into that diſmall <hi>Pagliarella</hi> or Cottage, where, as before<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> every ſtepp of her wandring abduction was but a variation of her unhappineſs; ſo now every minute of her abode in one place, is to produce, if not more, at leaſt greater misfortunes; for dureing his Commoration in this place, ſhe is encounter'd with neceſſities as well as force, and inward perplexities of minde, as well as outward inconveniencies of body, in relation whereof I ſhall be brief, leaſt they prove as troubleſome to you as they were greivous to her; For I am aſſured that neither you nor this auditory could eaſily ſwallow the tediousneſs of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhould I handle all at length, for long diſcourſes will not be received by them ſo eaſily as <hi>Welſh-women</hi> ſwallow down Flummery, nor would they all be as eaſily credited by a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red auditory, for they are indeed much like the Cloyſters of the Temple whereof a <hi>Greek</hi> Author ſaith thus <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> as incredible to thoſe who ſaw them not, as they were an amazement to thoſe who did but much more to the aflicted ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer whoſe abode in that place was like that of Purgatory where <hi>durante Commoratione</hi> there is nothing but torture and forment, for here ſhe did not only ſuffer under a totall disfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of all accomodations fitting for a perſon of her quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as want of competent fire to oppoſe the rigid ſeaſon of the year, food to uphold her, and convenient bedding to repoſe her ſelfe on, but alſo ſhe was Moleſted with terrours of death and other horrible affrightments, but theſe were nothing in reſpect, of what ſhe firſt ſuſpected in the agitation of her minde and afterwards found too true in the event, for not only the care of preſerving her Virginity pierced her Brain, but alſo the fear of looſing it transfixt her heart, but what was worſt of all is yet to be ſpoken off whereunto I ſhall diſcend by degrees, hoping that you will pardon my Language, if it chance to be ſullyed in the repreſentation of ſo foul a fact for as it will not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34205:11"/>become me to adulterat truth in the deſcription of a rape; ſo I muſt not Mutilat my Clients cauſe in cutting off any thing that is eſſentially requiſite yet it ſhall not be ſaid of me as it was ſaid of <hi>Zazius, Verbis inquinatis ſignificantibus tamen utebatur,</hi> noe, I ſhall rather decline propiety of terms in repreſentation of <hi>obſcene</hi> actions for they are in ſome ſort like the verity of faith which as <hi>Actiſiadorenſis obſerues, auctores melius exprimunt per vocem non ſignificatiuam quam per vocem ſignificatiuam,</hi> at the firſt entrance into the houſe ſhe found the now Defendent in a feveriſh fervour of minde, as ſullen as a Bull-finch, and as ſurly as a Lyon, evaporating like <hi>Elna</hi> or <hi>Mongibello</hi> out of his inflamed bowels the diſcontented paſſions of his diſappont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ambition, ſhortly after his countenace and undecent ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures did interpret his deſign to violate her Virgin Modeſty, which more clearly after appeared, by the more expreſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of his words, ſoliciting her to unchaſt imbraces, whereby ſhe feared, that he having gon ſo far, would not finde reſt but in extreams, thefore her Caution put a ſtrict watch on his behaviour all that day having as great a regard to every of his motions as Aſtrologers have to the Planet Dominant, and and when night began to wrapp them in darkneſs from the eye of the world, ſhe being more willing to prevent raviſhing by Death then to ſurvive raviſht, and being as fearful that her weakned body had not ſufficient power to reſiſt, as ſhe was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured ſhe had not patience to indure the dishonour of a rape, ſhe reſolved to be her own Executioner, chooſing rather to caſt her ſelf headlong, into the dark-Dungeon of the Grave, then to ſubmit, as a tame ſacrifice to his luſt: wherefore ſhe made a ſhift to convey into the ſtraw that was aſſign'd unto her for her bed, a Sword, with intention either to diſtroy him or her ſelf in caſe he ſhould dangerouſly attemmpt her Chaſtity.</p>
                  <p>Obſerve I beſeech you, <hi>Joſeph</hi> did leave his cloak behind him (in a ſtrumpets hand, rather then he would yield to her lewd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34205:11"/>inticements, <hi>Lucretia</hi> ſuffered Raviſhment, and afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came her own Executioner, but this grand exemplar and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime patern of Chaſtity, whoſe fear did produce effects of courage, being as willing to part with her life, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was to forſake his Garment, to preſerve her Chaſtity, the richeſt Jewel of the female ſex, did ſo farr exceed <hi>Lucretia</hi> the wonder of Roman Chaſtity, that ſhe did not onely chooſe freely to give up her life, by a Noble Anticipation, to prevent that miſchief which <hi>Lucretia</hi> ſurvived, but alſo would rather have expired in a generous reſiſtance then ſuffer the hazard of a diſgracefull Succubition and Compreſſion, I am not willing to arreſt your attention with any long diſcourſe foraign to a bare Narrative of the matter of Fact, yet before I proceed further therein I ſhall begg leave to interpoſe a ſhort parentheſis in juſtification of the Ladies intention in particular, and of their practice who have haſtened their own death, to prevent the intollerable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of Raviſhment, hopeing it will not be accounted a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome or uſeleſs digreſſion,</p>
                  <p>I ſhall therefore in a word or two humbly offer to your ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious cenſure, what I conceive is at this time ſuitable to that ſubject, and may ſerve for the future to conduct the conſcience in any caſe where perſons ſhall be reduced to the deplorable election, of ſuffering Raviſhment, or of laying violent hands on themſelves.</p>
                  <p>I know that the learned <hi>Taylor</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Down,</hi> in his caſes of Conſcience doth ſo much cry down a voluntary dying to preſerve chaſtity, that he ſaith it is no other thing then to ſin to avoid ſin, which he compares to <hi>Fannius</hi> his caſe of fear,
<q>
                        <l>Mortiſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> timorem,</l>
                        <l>Morte fugant ultroque vocant venientia fata.</l>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:34205:12"/>and making uſe of theſe words of St. <hi>Chriſoſtome to leap into the Sea for fear of Ship wrack, and to dye before the wound is given,</hi> he at laſt concludes in this compariſon that to do violence to our body to preſerve it chaſte is as the burning of a Temple to prevent its being profaned, he might have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed himſelf as elegantly in the words of the now Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in another caſe, if he had reſembled ſuch an act by the ſtarting horſe, that to ſhun a ſhadow lept into a precipice. I know alſo that St. <hi>Hierome</hi> on theſe words, <hi>Jonas. i. Mittile me in Mare</hi> expreſſeth himſelf thus much in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of that learned Biſhops opinion, <hi>non eſt noſtrum, mortem arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſed illatam ab aliis accipere, unde &amp; in Perſecutionibus nonlicet propria manu perire,</hi> that is to ſay, we muſt not ſnatch death with our own hands, but receive it when it is impos'd by others, and therefore in perſecutions we muſt not dye by our own hands, ſo much St. <hi>Hierome</hi> in defence of the Biſhop.</p>
                  <p>I cannot Iuſtifie the Ladies intention but in oppoſing the Biſhops opinion, and by anſwering the allegation of St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> which ſeems in the ſound of vvords to make ſo much for him.</p>
                  <p>To anſvver therefore the allegation out of St. <hi>Hierome</hi> is a thing that vvill eaſily be done, for the limitation of his vvords by an exceptive clauſe immediatly ſubjoyned to vvhat is alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, viz, <hi>non licet propria perire manu</hi> running in theſe precize terms viz, <hi>abſque eo ubi Caſtitas periclitatur,</hi> brings St. <hi>Hierome</hi> to my ſide, and declares him oppoſite to the Biſhop, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the judgment of that ancient and moſt learned Father, be as vveighty a teſtimony to Truth as the opinion of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; I need ſay no more to bring both Scales at leaſt to a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapeſo</hi> or <hi>aequilibrium;</hi> but to vveigh down the ſame vvith more preſſure of argument on our ſide, I ſhall caſt in a <hi>ſoprapeſo</hi> compacted of Law, illuſtrious examples and due applauſe of thoſe who in ſuch ſtreights have haſtned their death.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34205:12"/>
                  <p>The Law is clearly expreſſed in the words of <hi>Paulus libro undecimo</hi> recited in the <hi>ff. l. iſti quidem. (). quod ſi dederit,</hi> where the ſubject being violation of Chaſtity, it is ſaid, <hi>viris bonis iſte metus Major quam mortis eſſe debeat. i. e.</hi> he that fears to looſe his Chaſtity, fears more juſtly then he who fears the loſs of life.</p>
                  <p>As for preſidents I ſhall not being into example thoſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o for leſs cauſes haſtned their deaths, as the Priſoner of whom <hi>Seneca</hi> tells us that being to be expoſed to wild Beaſts in the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atre, he broke his neck in the ſpondels of the Wheele where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was drawn; nor <hi>Sampſon Saul</hi> or <hi>Razis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> who are uſually alledged as common Vouchers to prove that a man may haſten his ovvn death.</p>
                  <p>Be pleaſed to recal into your Memory that vvhich Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> if he vvere alive could not deny; That vvhen the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> broke into <hi>Livonia,</hi> and in their ſacking of the City <hi>Wenden</hi> uſed all manner of Cruelties, and Barbarous imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to Men and Women, filling all the ſtreets and houſes vvith blood and Luſt, a great many of the Citizens then run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Caſtle, blevv up themſelves vvith their Wives and Children to prevent thoſe horrours and flames of luſt, which they abhorred more then death.</p>
                  <p>I am ſure you cannot forget the example of <hi>Pelagia</hi> mentioned by St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> vvhich comes home to our caſe. <hi>Pelagia virgo quindecim annos nata ſponte ſibi necem maturavit, parata quidem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rat ad Cruciatus tormenta<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp; omne ſuppliciorum genus perferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ſed metuebat ne virgininatis Coronam perderet, i. e.</hi> She being a Virgin of fifteen years of age, of her ovvn accord ſhe haſtned death to her ſelf, ſhe vvas indeed ready to have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered all ſorts of moſt exquiſite Torments, but ſhe vvould not looſe the Crovvn of her Virginity.</p>
                  <p>So much may ſerve for the Legality and illuſtrious Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, of haſtening Death to prevent Violation of Chaſtity.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:34205:13"/>
                  <p>I ſhall now make it appear that it is not only lavvfull and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to good examples, but a ſo juſt and very commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from the further diſcourſe of St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> on that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, hence you may perceive ſaith he, that the luſt of wicked Hangmen ſtruck fear into <hi>Pelagia,</hi> and therefore from their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious luſt the Maiden removed and ſnatcht her ſelf, having had a juſt cauſe by her Voluntary death to prevent ſo great an injury, as the loſs of her Virginity: it is alſo reported by <hi>Laurentius Muller</hi> that the Act of the forementioned <hi>Livo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> who haſted their own deaths to eſcape the luſt of the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> was by the reſt of their Countrymen, and even by the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> themſelves reputed Excellent and admirable, and Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> himſelf confeſſeth that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the book <hi>Macabees</hi> Commends with great applauſe the of <hi>Razia</hi> as glorious and great.</p>
                  <p>I having thus ſhewed you that the preſervation of Chaſtity by Voluntary death may be juſtified by Law practiſed by Saints, &amp; commended by great good &amp; wiſe men; I ſhall now only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve unto you that the laſt Conſideration which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of good holy and learned men, is the prime Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the ſame Biſhop uſeth to legitimate the Stratagem of a lye, or the prevaricateing with a ſullen truth, to ſave a a mans life, in his caſes of Conſcience <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>And now I am to return from this digreſſion into the direct path of proſecuting my Narrative in which I may novv juſtly tell you that her intention had undoubtedly ſucceeded in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution had not her treacherous Maid novv apperaing an exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Agent in the affaires of abomination privily tooke avvay the ſvvord vvhich vvas ſheathed above the hilt in the Stravv, vvhereby ſhe became diſabled to offend him or defend herſelf. I obſerve that the Auditory is already tranſported into admira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, but I ſhall ſay as did <hi>Charicleia</hi> in <hi>Heliodorus</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>i.e.</hi> Do ye vvonder at theſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34205:13"/>things? theſe are yet greater which I am to relate: After this, ſhe being much waſted by the abundant ſhedding of tears which ſome <hi>Philoſophers</hi> tearm the ſweat of an afflicted heart, and the exceſſive decay of her ſpirits by long wakeing, and relying upon the ſworn promiſe of her Maids watchfulneſs, and the preſumed humanity of the Family, ſhe compoſed her ſelf to a poſture of reſt, but alas the ſleep of <hi>Condemned Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls,</hi> and of women begirt with a ſtreight Seige by a <hi>Barbarous</hi> Enemy was not more diſturbd then hers, for that which ſhould have afforded her reſt to the reparation of her ſtrength, ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only to affright her imagination: untill at laſt in reality ſhe found her ſelf ſurprized by a Barbarous attempt of the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to raviſh her, ſhe then in that Conflict ſought for the Inſtrument of Death in the Straw, but found quickly that it was ſubtracted by her Maid, ſhe was then plunged into a moſt deſperat perplexity of mind, which had been enough to have ſwallowed all hopes of help had not her Vigorous reluctancy been ſeconded with an accident which hapned at that very time, which was a ſud dain raging ſire that took hold on the Thatch of the houſe. Though ſhe then eſcaped the danger by quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Luxuriant heate of his imodeſt deſires <hi>per jgnis appoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem</hi> yet you may well imagin what direfull impreſſions of fear and horrour, were begotten in the timorous minde of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſed Lady, for then ſhe wiſht that the happie accident which had put fire to the houſe, had alſo put her adverſary into a flameing combuſtion: or that by a ſuddain incineration it had reduced her into Aſhes. When the flame ceaſed, and her affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted minde remained under the terrour of theſe imaginations, her Treacherous Maid faced with the Vizar of a ſmiling countenance perſwaded her again to repair unto her reſt, aſſuring her that ſhe would lye by her, and with her vigilancy and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance would ſecure her from the violence of the Defendent. wherefore being ready to faint in her ſpirits for want of ſleep
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34205:14"/>ſhe ſuffered her ſelfe to be perſwaded to yeild to that which ſhe perceived unreſiſtably ſeizing upon her, but the Maid which ſhould have been her preſervation proved her deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, inſomuch that it was then with her as it was once with the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Siege of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> according to the words of a <hi>Perſian</hi> Author, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>remedium vitae cauſa mortis erat</hi> they both therefore lye upon the Bed of Straw, and after a while, the Maid moſt traiterouſly withdraws her ſelf after the manner of <hi>Piantone</hi> which is <hi>partire ſenza licenza e abandonare un amico,</hi> to part without takeing leave; and like a thorough paced Beaſt in iniquity yeilds her place to the libidinous Defendent: who ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized the perſon of my ſlumbring Client with all endeavour he could uſe to deprive her of her pretious Virginity: ſhe then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakned rather to an amazement then out of Sleep reſiſted him with the greateſt oppoſition ſhe could make, crying out for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, whilſt her Maid behaved her ſelf as an unconcern'd perſon, as if ſhe had been one of the Daughters of <hi>Martinus Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> or of the Family of the <hi>Achtsniets</hi> the people of the houſe terrified by ſo great a force as was then over them, gave noe help to her; but rather with a Cowardly ſilence ſeemed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that villanous fact; which otherwiſe I believe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Charity they would have loudly declaim'd againſt, dure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which time alſo his accurſed Complices not only encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged him in the purſuit of his luſt by polluted diſcourſes, more loathſom then the ſulphurious evaporations of Hell, uſeing ſuch words as might have moved <hi>Lucretia Portia</hi> or <hi>Penelope</hi> to Luxury, but alſo helpt him &amp; diſabled her in ſuch Barbarous manner as that I may modeſtly expreſs my ſelf only in the words of <hi>Hydaſpes</hi> to <hi>Claricleja dicere non poſſum caeterum vobis relinquo Conſider andum,</hi> at laſt having benum'd her Senſes with the bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all her limbs as if he had been of the opinion which was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34205:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>tracqued to an eminent Perſon yet liveing by a Curteſan of honour in Rome, called <hi>Nina Barcarola</hi> who not being ſo curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to that Perſon as to others, he caus'd her to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely whipt in Rome, whereupon ſhe writ a letter unto him ſetting forth that the reaſon of his ſeverity to her, was, that he might take the more delight in her, for as much as <hi>Carne battuta</hi> was <hi>piu ſaporita</hi> fleſh that was beaten was moſt ſavory.</p>
                  <p>Now the two Combatants as it were intangled in a Cloſe, ſhe was overmatcht by the prevalent force of his Luſt; which govern'd the functions of his Libidinous limbs, and he like a ſtiffned pillar tooke ſuch advantage of her imbecillity, that breaking the Seal of her ſecrets he blaſted the verdent Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of her Virginity by Carnal knowledge of her, in which act as it was ſaid of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12th of <hi>France</hi> his acting with his Queen, he did rather poſſeſs then enioy her, for I am moſt Conſident upon the Credit of her own relation and other inducements of belief, that She tooke no more pleaſure in that Compreſſion and Coniungment, then a toothleſs Old woman would have done in chewing an hard cruſt. Manycir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of this foul fact I am forced to put into oblivion for want of tearms to expreſs them and my words faile me &amp; I want expreſſion to ſet forth her reſentments of them, yet it is eaſy for you to conceive in what manner ſhe lamented the rigour of her misfortunes reflecting as well on the ſhame of her living friends as on the memory of thoſe deceaſed: for as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaid of <hi>Nepotianus,</hi> ô <hi>Faelix Nepotianus qui haec non videt,</hi> ſo may ſhe ſay of her good Mother and her Honourable Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father lately deceaſed, whoſe memory remains and will alwaies be preſerved in honour, that they were ſeaſonably taken off the Stage of this world before this miſery might have befallen them, for undoubtedly they would have ſhrunk into horrour to have ſeen this day.</p>
                  <p>The matter is not yet ended, much is reſerued for the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34205:15"/>latter Scene of this prodigious Tragedie, for the Complices of the Defendent do now boiſterouſly endeavour to perſwade her, that the only means to remedy this Blemiſh and to repair the ruins of her Fame, was to joyne the Ordinance of God to ſo foul a fact and to marry with the Defendent; but ſhe though in the depth of her perplexities was judiciouſly convinc't that to have married him afterwards, was, but to turn a green wound into a Fiſtula or an <hi>Exulceration,</hi> and therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted againſt it with as great deteſtation as ſhe could expreſs, whilſt the Defendent ſeem'd rather to boaſt of, then to bluſh at ſo foul a fact.</p>
                  <p>You are now inform'd of a rape ſo Barbarous, ſo prodigious, that if it were poſſible to collect the voices of all Nations together, the Defendent would be Condemned by the ſuffrages of all mankind, unleſs the <hi>Enormonſneſs</hi> of the fact might authoriſe his Crime, or he might be made innocent, by the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that did mainly aggravate it; or unleſs his force were as able to abrogate as to break the Law: for of all vices apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Fleſh ſaith <hi>Ottauiano Zuccaro, non é niſſuno vitio checon eſſo ſeco porti piu puzzolente infamia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am now to informe you that the Defendent at laſt thinks it neceſſary to overſpred with forged pretences, the broad face of ſo great a Crime, and therefore he would palliat the rape under the colour of Marriage with the <hi>Actrix. Nov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atus</hi> conſecrated himſelf a Biſhop, and the Defendent might as well have Married himſelf, if Coniugall relations might have been made up <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> but that would not ſerve his turn, he wants two things, firſt of all the conſent of my Client, ſecondly Celebration of Marriage: the firſt he endeavoured, but found it too difficult to obtain, the latter he thought eaſie to Compaſs by a forged Licence, he therefore in the firſt place applyes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to her by all Arguments he could take from the ordinary and known topicks of perſwaſion to gaine her Conſent, but ſhe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34205:15"/>refuſing Complyance, he caſt a diſmall Frown on his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and in moſt furious accents of ſpeech menaced her, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to ſend her to <hi>Gallway,</hi> and ſomtimes threatned her with expatriation, telling her that he would immediatly ſend her into <hi>France</hi> by a Ship then in her view, which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended he had prepared for that purpoſe, all this did not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, therefore he reſorts to his inſtrument of force that <hi>incutiendo timorem,</hi> he might at leaſt ſcrew her up <hi>ad conſenſum non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictionis,</hi> &amp; prevails by what means I am unwilling to inſtance in, with a Prieſt, to attempt Marrying of them, in pronouncing ſome words of the Office of Matrimony, which he did utter, notwithſtanding that ſhe had by many abſolute words and expreſs and infallible ſignes (and in particular as you have heard by throwing with contempt the ring forceably pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on her finger into the chimny) made ſufficient indications of her diſſent, even then when the Frowns of many angry and menaceing foreheads would have reſtrain'd her from the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of a <hi>plenary Contradiction.</hi> The matter being thus done, he knew well enough that it was not the looſing of Virginity but conjugal allyance that made a Marryage: for it is a rule of law that <hi>nuptias non concubitus ſed conſenſus facit,</hi> he was alſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficietly perſwaded that the words of a Prieſt do not operat any thing as to the Celebration of Marriage without the lawful conſent and mutual union of wills, and that the Prieſt could do no more without he conſent in this caſe then if <hi>Poncio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nello</hi> had acted the part of a Prieſt, yet he being deſirous as I ſaid before to Cover his offence, and perhaps ſtirred up ſome what by his diſappointed paſſion, to conſult with malice that reſtleſs Hag and Mother of calumny, he endeavours by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique impreſſions of Calumnious jactitations, at ſeveral times and in ſundry places to make the world believe that ſhe was his Lawful Wife, and to inſinuate it vvith the greater <hi>veriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude</hi> into the beleef of the <hi>populareſe</hi> he cauſed ſeveral let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34205:16"/>to be vvritten intimateing a pretended Marriage, at laſt he brings her to the Tovvn poorer then a Carthuſian and lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then a <hi>Romiſh lent,</hi> vvith intention to keep her ſecretly within his povver untill he might aſſure himſelf of her affection, but at her firſt entrance into the Tovvn ſhe vvas by Gods providence ſo happie as to meet a friend of hers, by vvhoſe happie aſſiſtance and the Lord of <hi>Arans</hi> favour and prudence ſhe vvas immediat-reſtored to liberty, and then ſhe began to act her Part. <hi>liberis habenis,</hi> and in the firſt place the ſame day ſhe came to Tovvn maks a proteſtation againſt the force and Injuries offered her in <hi>Authentique</hi> forme of Lavv, which as it was not poſſible to do it ſooner, ſo ſhe could not well have delayed it longer.</p>
                  <p>Sir: I know that Calumny is leſs regarded ſince it became ſo commonly interwoven in the dialect of theſe times, and that it was never very operative with wiſe men, where it was not accompanied with an opinion of ſincerity in the Author, and I likewiſe know that this Calumny of jactitation of Marryage with my Client, is but a lying imputation proceeding from the diſappointed ambition of him, who is but a profligat perſon, whoſe breath is ſufficient almoſt to infect the aire and ſtayn the glory of the ſtars, yet my Client ſeeming thereby to be ſully<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in her Credit, which touches her in in the tendereſt and moſt inward part of her concernment, and being as unwilling to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal her misfortune as ſhe was unable to lye under the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo foul a Calumny in this Age, wherein moſt eares are as Credulous as his tongue is licentious, applyes her ſelf to this honourable Court, as the proper and free ſtreaming Fountain of Iuſtice, wherein ſhe now caſts her ſelf to waſh out the ſtains of her wounded reputation, and hopes that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendent being overwhelm'd at laſt under the burthen of his Crimes will find the Cataſtrophe of his pretenſions partly in the doom of this Court and partly in the juſt ſeverity of the Common Law.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:34205:16"/>
                  <p>Sir I have faithfully, though not curiouſly guided you by the Torch of truth into the knowledge of the matter of fact, and in my relation thereof I am confident that I have not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed any thing but your patience, with which alſo I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, in the omitting of many aggravations more then circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial againſt the Defendant, and though I ſhould now by a cleer ſhewing forth of evidence confirm every particular of what I have preſented unto you, yet to recompence in ſome ſort the length of my Narrative with the brevity of what I am to ſpeake of, we are reſolved to apply the evidence to no more points of controverſie then are abſolutely neceſſary to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the two great Articles viz, that there was not, nor could be any lawfull marriage contracted or celebrated between the Actrix and the Defendant from the time of the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and abduction untill her reſtitution to liberty in regard of the force and fear which continued all that time upon her, and that he is guilty of a ſcandalous jactitation of marriage for which he deſerves to be firſt chaſtiſed with the ſevereſt rodds of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical diſcipline, and then to be tranſmitted a <hi>Conſiſtorio ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ad praetorium Regis. i. e.</hi> from the Court Chriſtian to the Kings Bench.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:34205:17"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:34205:17"/>
                  <p>The Caſe of <hi>Mrs MARY WARE,</hi> and IAMES SHIRLY;</p>
                  <p>As it was argued, Relating to the ſeveral points of Law incident unto, and emergent there out</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Dudley Loftus</hi> LL.D. in the conſiſtory Court before Dr: <hi>Willam Buckley</hi> Chancellor to the Arch Biſhop of Dublin, in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> tearm 1668.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN.</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the Kings Moſt Exel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſty for <hi>Samuel Dancer</hi> Bookſeller in Caſtleſtreet.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:34205:18"/>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:34205:18"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE have now reduced the matter of fact to its true ſpecies, and you may be pleaſed to obſerve, that we have proved with legal and ſufficient evidence ſo much thereof in this cauſe as is requiſite to the founding of our intention, for we have eſtabliſhed beyond all contradiction the verity of the following particulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt the abduction of the Actrix by the Defendant and his complices <hi>vi armatâ</hi> on the Twenty Seventh of <hi>January</hi> 1668. and that the <hi>Actrix</hi> or the <hi>vim paſſa</hi> from the time of that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction untill her reſtitution to liberty in this City, continued under the force &amp; terrour of the Defendant and his complices.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, That during the continuance of that force upon her, ſhe was moſt barbarouſly Raviſht by the Defendant.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, That immediatly upon her reſtitution to liberty ſhe did proteſt in due form of law againſt the ſaid force, and all Acts whatſoever done or ſuffered by her to her prejudice during that inter-ſpace of time as invalid, and of no force to binde an obligation upon her.</item>
                     <item>Fourthly, That the Defendant hath in a moſt vain glorious <hi>Jactitation</hi> boaſted that a marriage was Celebrated between him and the <hi>Actrix</hi> during the time ſhe was under that force and terrour.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>I ſhould now ſpeake to ſuch points of Law as are convenient to be applyed and fitly adjuſted to the ſeveral matters of fact ſo proved; but in regard ſome circumſtances of what was acted during the force ſeems to reſt upon the Teſtimony of the <hi>Actrix,</hi> I ſhall firſt of all bring good Corroboration thereunto
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34205:19"/>from undeniable Authorities of law, whereby it will appear in great viſibility that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> her own Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is ſufficient evidence in that or the like caſes. My firſt argument carries with it the weight of an undenyable Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which is the opinion of <hi>Hyppolitus de Marſiliis</hi> a famous Juriſt <hi>tractatu de fide juſſoribus p.</hi> 614. <hi>num.</hi> 178, who ſaith <hi>de damno dato ſtatur ſacramento damnum paſſi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, I know that a ſingle opinion is uſually accompted but the ſuperficial glittering of a ſlight argument, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore add unto the former Authority the atteſtation of <hi>Panor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitan.</hi> extra <hi>de his quae vi metuſue cauſa fiunt Cap. ult:</hi> where we have theſe words, <hi>probatâ violentiâ res amiſſae probantur per juramentum, &amp; ſecuto petentis juramento ſit condemnatio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, I ſhall make uſe in the next place of the Authority of <hi>Chaſſanaeus</hi> in his commentaries in <hi>Conſuetudines Burgundiae p.</hi> 61. where he expreſly declares that <hi>Statur juramento Virginis contra deflorantem,</hi> which words are ſo appoſite and compleat that they need no addition, and ſo evident as that they want no interpretation.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, I ſhall urge another Authority as cleer and as full as any of the former, but of more aſſured determination, and ſo powerfully convincing that there can be no evaſion from it, and that is taken from the Sacred leaves of Holy writ, <hi>Deutre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy</hi> the 22th and the 24th where <hi>Grotius</hi> in his annotations referring to his book <hi>de jure Belli ac pacis lib.</hi> 2d. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.12. ſaith <hi>lex Hebraea puellae de vi illata in agro credi vult.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Though ſo cleer and full Authorities as I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed need not be ſupplyed by former preſidents or juſtified by inſtances of former judicial deciſions; yet becauſe examples are indeed the life and light of natural reaſon, and are the beſt fortifications in all controverſies of this nature, I ſhall produce one or two preſidents, the firſt is the caſe of Biſhop <hi>Januarius</hi> 2. q. 1. Cap. <hi>imprimis</hi> (.) <hi>Glorioſus,</hi> where <hi>Glorioſus Comitiolus</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:34205:19"/>was ordered by decree, to reſtore and make recompence unto Biſhop <hi>Januarius,</hi> whatſoever he ſhould prove, by his own Oath, to have loſt or ſuffered whileſt he was under force and terrour, <hi>quicquid praedictus Epiſcopus per violentiam at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> inſecutionem ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us expendiſſe, vel damnum pertuliſſe, dato ſacramento firmave rit iidem epiſcopo reſtituendum condemnetur,</hi> where you may obſerve the very Image of our caſe, for the <hi>vim paſſus</hi> is admitted to prove his wrong and intereſt meerly by his own Oath, and the reaſon is well rendred in the gloſs, <hi>hoc ideo eſt, quia res talis aliter nequit probari,</hi> to the ſame purpoſe you may conſult the <hi>Code de fide inſtrumentorum l</hi> (.) <hi>ultima.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixthly, Again you have another the like caſe among thoſe which are termed <hi>caſus longi Bernardi,</hi> extra <hi>de his quae vi metu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue cauſa fiunt cap. ſuper eo,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>quidam dicebat ſe ſpoliatum fuiſſe a quibuſdam adverſariis ſuis per violentiam, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit illos in judicio, lite conteſtatâ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> probavit ſolummodo per proprie um juramentum, ſingula quae amiſerat, ſed de violentia ſibi illata, probavit per teſtes, &amp; ſic condemnati fuerunt,</hi> and this condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation was afterwards confirmed in the decretals by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, I ſhall add no more for proof of this point, for whatſoever is offered above the heaped meaſure of a plenary probation is to be eſteemed as no more then a learned extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie.</p>
                  <p>So much for the cleering of our evidence, there is one thing more which I muſt offer to conſideration before I proceed to the main deſciſſory points of Law, and that is the juſtification of our proceedings.</p>
                  <p>I know no objection of moment that can be raiſed againſt the regularity and ſufficiency of our proceedings in this cauſe, yet to anſwer the greateſt Cavill that hath been made againſt us, I muſt take notice of what Doctor <hi>French</hi> hath ſpoken <hi>quoad litis ordinativa,</hi> I conceive it was a vaſt degeneration from ancient and Canonical practice, that he ſhould have had admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34205:20"/>to ſpeake in the behalf of the Defendant not onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced Contumacious, but alſo excommunicated if not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed, I do not mention this ſo much by way of complaint, as to put you in mind of what he ſaid in a word or two, for though he ſpoke often yet he ſtarted but one objection, and that was onely to oppoſe the manner of our proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Defendant for that he was not perſonally cited, this objection he often retrived and as paſſionatly urged it againſt us, and no wonder, for it ſeem'd like <hi>Sampſons</hi> lock wherein his whole ſtrength lay, it hath been formerly disſheveled, and it is now to be cutt off by a total abſciſion, to the which end I ſhall bring it to the teſt of Law and reaſon.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall never oppoſe any thing which I think is true, and therefore I muſt not deny ſo refulgent a truth as is the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of a Citation in all judiciary proceedings at leaſt between party and party, which is not onely founded in the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but alſo by all other lawes owned and approved of as <hi>fundamentum juditii,</hi> for which reaſon the <hi>Clementine Paſtoralis de ſententia &amp; re judicata</hi> declares in the caſe between <hi>Henry</hi> the Emperour and <hi>Robert</hi> King of <hi>Sicilia</hi> that <hi>ſententia dici non meruit quae a judice in abſent em nec citatum legitimé, ac inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum, &amp; per conſequens indefenſum lata fuit,</hi> which doctrine is alſo moſt cleerly expreſſed 33.92. cap. <hi>ſecularis &amp;</hi> 36.96. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite multorum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But whether a perſonal Citation be neceſſary in all caſes or particularly in this, is the queſtion, for reſolution whereof in the negative, I might urge the indulgence of the law <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ff. de Excuſationibus</hi> made by <hi>Antonius Augustinus,</hi> which gives way to Cite perſons <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>perſonaliter aut domi ſuae,</hi> which is as we uſe to ſay perſonally or by a <hi>viis &amp; modis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is apparent upon inſpection into this law that I do not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alledge the words, and that they ſound cleerly conſonant to this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34205:20"/>note; that in caling of perſons to Judgement we may chooſe whether we will Cite them perſonally to appear, or Summon them in by <hi>a viis &amp; modis</hi> for the words are <hi>alternate</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>perſonaliter aut domi ſuae</hi> and in <hi>alternatiues,</hi> it is well known that the debtor, or he who is to performe the obligation is to have his election, for ſaith the law <hi>ſi plura alternativé ſeu disjunctim adſcripta ſint unum adim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plere ſufficit, ut obligationi ſatisfactum videatur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But for as much as I ſhould ſeeme to ſtrain this Law too far and urge it further then our Caſe requires, by ſerueing up the ſence thereof <hi>ad montem literae</hi> (for it would be as abſur'd that the perſon ſhould not be perſonally Cited where he may be had, as it would be irrational to require that he ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally ſummoned where he cannot be found: I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſupply out of the principles of right reaſon the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law where it ſeems defective, and accommodat the the words to a perfect underſtanding, and directly to our proper Caſe, by diſtinguiſhing between <hi>alternatues of ſimyle Election, and alernatives of preorditat diſpoſiion;</hi> an alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native of ſimple Election is where a perſon or perſons obliged to performe any two or more things, may, without being Confined to any order of Election make choiſe of which he will to ſatisfie his obligation, as for Example if I oblige my ſelf to pay unto <hi>Titius</hi> at a certain day, an hundred Barrells of wheat, or in lieuthereof, an hundred pounds ſterl: it is then in my Choyfe to pay which I will, and by the payment of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am totally diſobliged(.)An alternative of preordinat E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection is when the payment or performance of one thing or an other may ſatisfie the Debt, yet ſo as that the one is pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily intended and required, and the other is not ſufficient unleſs ſubſidiarily upon the failing of the former, as for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, by the Civil Lavv ſince the Epiſtle of <hi>Divus Hadrianus,</hi> (the Emperour and not <hi>Pope Hadrian</hi> the 4th as <hi>Fuller</hi> in his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34205:21"/>Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory misapprehends) became of force, the Creditor may ſue the principal Debtor, or his ſureties, but cannot ſue the ſuretie <hi>niſi excuſſo principali</hi> unleſs the fideiuſſor hath renounced the benefit of that Epiſtle, ſo it is in our Caſe, vve had liberty to Cite the Defendent perſonally or by a <hi>viis &amp; modis</hi> but vvere limited by ſuch courſe of preordinat Election, as that vve could not Cite him by <hi>viis &amp; modis</hi> ſo long as we could have ſerved him perſonally, ſo that <hi>Panormitau Capite cauſam Extra de dolo &amp; Contumacia</hi> n. 5. ſaith <hi>Citatio debet primo fieri in perſona ſi poſſibile eſt, alias fit domi,</hi> and therefore <hi>Hiſtienſis</hi> quoted by <hi>Panormitantit. eodem</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſi in provincia eſt debet citari perſonaliter ubicunque reperiatur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The queſtion therefore vvill be vvhether the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendent vvere to be found or no for if he were not to be found in <hi>Provintia,</hi> it is moſt certaine that a <hi>viis &amp; modis</hi> vvithout any perſonal Citation may be deemed ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and legal enough, as I ſhall prove by the <hi>ſubſequent</hi> allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vvhich are ſo cleer and manifeſt in the point, that no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry or prevarication can vvreſt them to another ſenſe.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall begin vvith <hi>Bouhick Capite cauſam. Extra. de dolo &amp; Contumacia,</hi> whoſe authority in this caſe is an evidence of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controulable Certaintie, he ſaith <hi>ſi aliquis non poteſt inveniri perſonaliter ad citandum in provincia, ſed bene extra. tune non eſt neceſſe eum perſonaliter citari, ſed perinde eſt ac ſi non poſſit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubi reperiri.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you will caſt more weight into the ſcales you may add hereunto many other Authorities as that of <hi>Panormitan. de dolo &amp; contumacia cap: ultimo</hi> n. 1. <hi>citatio fit ad eccleſiam citandi quando non reperitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again the ſame Author affords another Teſtimony to the ſome purpoſe as cleer as the former, <hi>capite inter quatuor. de Majoritate &amp; obedientia. pro Citato habetur ille qui ſe occultat ut non poſſit Citari,</hi> and this agreeth with the Doctrine of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretal. <hi>cap: quoniam (.) porro, ut lite non conteſtata non procedatur,</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:34205:21"/>Which is ſo cleer that it will leave no place for further doubt or ſcruple — <hi>porró ſpeciales cauſae poſſunt occurrere in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus caſualiter eſt aliud obſervandum: ut verbi gratia: ſi ſuper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licujus Electione, vel copula maritali quoeſtio moveatur: tunc etenius no propter longam moram in Spiritualibus &amp; temporalibus patiatur eccleſia laeſionem: vel viro ſeu mulieri fornicationis occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio praebeatur: in huiuſmodi caſibus, ſi contumax apparuerit is; in quem actio fuit dirigenda ſeu quia peremtoria citatione recepta, venire contemnit: ſeu quia malitioſe ſcipſum occultat: ſeu quiae impedit ne poſſit a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l eum citatio pervenire: teſtes, lite non conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata, ſunt merito admittendi, &amp; nihilominus ſi de cauſa liquat ad diffinitivam ſententiam procedendum,</hi> hence the gloſs upon the word <hi>impedit</hi> obſerveth, <hi>talis habetur pro citato denunciatione facta publicè ad do mumſuam,</hi> and his obſervation is there illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſeveral quotations <hi>Cap: ex tuae, de cle: non reſid: de dolo &amp; contumacia cap: ult:</hi> and for further illuſtration he there ſaith <hi>&amp; ita ſufficit quod publicè edictum proponatur ad domum ſuam vel ad eccleſiam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Furthermore I conceive that where a <hi>litis conteſtation</hi> is not neceſſary, there, a perſonal Citation for one vvho is <hi>extra pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciam</hi> is not requiſite; but in caſes vvhere there is a diſpute <hi>de faedere Matrimonii,</hi> there is no neceſſity of a <hi>Litis conteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> as appears in <hi>Bouhick de lite non Conteſtata, Capite. quoniam fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter,</hi> by an argument taken a <hi>ſenſu contrario,</hi> for there he ſaith <hi>aut non agitur de faedere Matrimonij, ſed de alio caſu puta adulterio vel hujuſmodi, &amp; tunc non eſt procedendum lite non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatâ,</hi> vvhence vve may vvarrantably conclude, that in this caſe vvhere a matter of marriage comes into queſtion, vve may preceed <hi>lite non conteſtata,</hi> and therefore vvithout a perſonal Citation.</p>
                  <p>Moreover <hi>ubi mora ſit periculum allatura</hi> there is no neceſſity of a <hi>Litis conteſtation,</hi> but ſuch a caſe as this vvill not ſuffer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, for the lavv doth ſuppoſe there may be <hi>periculum fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:34205:22"/>in caſe a young woman in <hi>fermento juventuis</hi> ſhould remain unmarried until the perſon vvere Cited perſonally, for vvhich reaſon ſaith <hi>Boubick tit &amp; cap. iiſdem</hi> paulo inferius <hi>in cauſes Matrimonialibus &amp; ipſas tangentibus indiſtincte procedi poteſt lite non conteſtatâ ad receptionem teſtium,</hi> the like you may ſee in the <hi>Clementine diſpendioſam de judiciis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Furthermore that I may baffle all oppoſition that can be made againſt us in this point, ſuffer me to add the Authority of celebrated <hi>Ruckerus</hi> in his <hi>conſilia Matrimonialia</hi> vvith his reaſon annexed, <hi>non eſt opus ut requiratur abſens extra provinciam ſeu civitatem, quia ſic eſſet proceſſus in infinitum,</hi> and for this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he there quotes <hi>Bartholus</hi> and others.</p>
                  <p>This opinion hath as you have heard the ſuffrages of the beſt Doctors and Gloſſaries, I ſhall therefore make no further addition in Corroboration thereof, for I think I have more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to beg pardon for having ſaid ſo much, then to ſay any more to prove that a perſonal Citation is unneceſſary in this caſe; I having novv removed the onely objections that could be ſurmiſed againſt our evidence and proceedings, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the main deciſſory points of lavv, and enter into a more cloſe and exact diſcuſſion of the Buiſineſs, and in the firſt place I ſhall ſpeake briefly <hi>de vi &amp; metu</hi> and ſhevv you firſt hovv they operat upon the vvill, ſecondly vvhat operation they have in this caſe as to point of lavv and impediment of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, as to the firſt give me leave for your better ſatisfaction to recall into your memory ſome Philoſophical notions vvhereby the violence offered to the vvill may be the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
                  <p>The principles of every thing may be reduced to a tvvofold difference, ſome are intrinſical as matter and form, ſome are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſical as the efficient and end.</p>
                  <p>Now, whatſoever belongeth to any thing according to its intrinſick principles cannot be termed violent, but onely that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34205:22"/>which ariſeth from principles extrinſick, ſo that there is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold extrinſick violence, one in reſpect of the efficient, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reſpect of the end, that which is violent in regard of the efficient, may be inſtanced in the motion of a ſtone or any heavie thing upward, that which is violent in reſpect of the end may be reſembled by one who being in iminent danger of ſhipwrack caſts his goods over board, being not violentated by any one <hi>per modum efficientis,</hi> but onely <hi>per modum finis,</hi> for that he would avoid the danger and ſo preſerve his life.</p>
                  <p>Now between theſe two ſorts of coaction there is a great difference, for coaction which is <hi>per modum efficientis</hi> is ſimply violent and involuntary having nothing of free will, as a ſtone in its projection upwards againſt its natural inclination.</p>
                  <p>But coaction which is <hi>per modum finis,</hi> becauſe it participats ſomewhat of that which is voluntary, is not ſimply or abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly violent, but onely <hi>ſecundum quid</hi> and ſuch a violence is called by the Philoſopher <hi>voluntarium permixium</hi> and as there is a twofold coaction ſo alſo is there a twofold agent capable of compulſion, the one natural, and that onely can be compelled <hi>per modum efficientis,</hi> as is a ſtone, for ſuch an agent, when it doth not act by coaction, acts by a form ſimply determin'd to one thing, the other is a free agent and that cannot be violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated nor compel'd <hi>per modum efficientis,</hi> but onely <hi>per modum finis,</hi> and ſuch a coaction may conſiſt with liberty ſimply, this diſtinction you have in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the 3d. of his Ethicks, where after his defining what is <hi>violentum,</hi> he gives an example of that which is violent <hi>per modum efficientis,</hi> as when the wind carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away a man againſt his will, an example of that which is violent <hi>ratione finis</hi> he ſubjoyns there viz, ſuch things as are wrought either by the fear of greater evils, or the love of a greater good, and of this ſecond not of the firſt doth he doubt whether it be voluntary or noe.</p>
                  <p>Now the will which is a free agent hath a twofold act viz,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34205:23"/>an immanent and interiour act as that of nilling and willing, and an exteriour imperat act as it is termed by the Schoolmen as the act of moveing the bodily members in <hi>Locomotion,</hi> as to the firſt act the will cannot be compelled by any thing <hi>per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum efficientis,</hi> but <hi>per modum finis,</hi> yet as to the exteriour acts it may be compel'd <hi>per modum efficientis,</hi> for it is moſt cleer that one may move the members of another mans body againſt his will.</p>
                  <p>I have now made it appear how the will may ſuffer violence by fear and force, in the next place I ſhall offer to conſideration what operation <hi>vis &amp; metus</hi> have in this caſe as to impediment of marriage. I ſhall now handle them apart, and firſt <hi>de metu,</hi> for <hi>quod metus cauſa geſtum erit ratum non habebo</hi> ſaith the <hi>Praetor ff. quod metus cauſa geſtum erit l.</hi> 1. but becauſe <hi>Labeo</hi> ſaith in this law, <hi>metum accipiendum non quemlibet ſed majoris malitatis.</hi> I will therefore firſt define fear by the common ſuffrages of Doctors and the Goſſaries to be <hi>inſtantis vel futuri periculi cauſa mentis trepidatio,</hi> and then diſtinguiſh thereof thus, there are three kinds of fear according to <hi>Zaſius Inſtitutionibus de actioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> (.) <hi>quadrupli,</hi> the firſt is a Concuſſive fear which proceeds from threats, and ſuch was the fear that poſſeſſed the mind of the actrix when the Defendent and his complices breathed out menaces to carry her to <hi>Galway,</hi> or to tranſport her into <hi>France</hi> unleſs ſhe would ſubmit to his deſire.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, an impreſſive fear which the Schoolmen and ſome Lawyers term <hi>metus facti,</hi> as when blowes are given or one is in reſtraint as my Client was when guarded in the time of her abduction by the Defendent and his <hi>Marmidons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, a compulſive fear, which proceeds a <hi>vi armata,</hi> and this was the terrour that affrighted the Actrix, ſo ſhe was firſt of all ſurprized and beſet in hoſtile manner by eight armed Horſemen, and by them or moſt of them guarded in all places
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34205:23"/>from the time of her ſaid abduction untill her reſtitution to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, with ſwords and Piſtols.</p>
                  <p>Thus much of the definition of fear &amp; the ſeveral kinds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as obſerved by <hi>Zaſius,</hi> I am now to ſhew you the operation of fear as to the annulling and impeding ſeveral acts &amp; particularly that of Marriage, fear excuſeth a man from the tye of a regular profeſſion, in ſo much that if one through fear be made to enter into religion he may freely return to his former ſecular condition <hi>cap perlatum extra de his quae vi metuſue cauſa</hi> where <hi>fiunt Barnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Summs</hi> up the caſe thus, A certaine Noble man holding his Wife in ſuſpition Commanded ſome Souldiers under his Command that they ſhould carry her to a Wood and there put her to death, They accordingly bring her to the Wood, but the ſword being drawn to execute that Command, the Souldiers moved with a generous &amp; pious Compaſſion tooke pitie on her, and ſpared her life on condition ſhe ſhould betake her ſelf to a Monaſtery and there aſſume the habit of a Nun; whereupon ſhe is led into a Monaſtery, the Knight her husband ſent two Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to the Monaſtery to impoſe on her the Veyle; the Biſhops taking into their grave Conſideration, that ſhe was a young woman and had a young Son, grew ſuſpitious of her change of life; they take her aſide den anding the reaſon of her tranſition into that State of life, ſhe therefore declaring the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in order, tould them that it proceeded meerly from feare of death; and that as ſoon as ſhe could ſhe would return into the world, the one of theſe Biſhops that he might ſeem to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisſie her husbands cruelty feigneth the puting on the Veile up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, after wards this Knight dyeth, the Wife then immediatly leaves the Monaſtery, and takes another husbands wherefore the Biſhop of the Dioceſe at the inſtance of the Nuns Excommunicated her, the injured Lady inſinuats the matter to the Pope, whereupon his Holyneſs delegats a power to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34205:24"/>Judges of abſolving her &amp; her husband from the Sentence of Excommunication, ſhe taking an oath <hi>eorum parere manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> and that then they ſhould call her, the <hi>Abiſſe</hi> and <hi>Nuns</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and if it ſhould appear by lawfull proof that ſhe had entred the Monaſtery not through fear of death but ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneouſly, or that notwithſtanding ſhe had entred by fear of death, ſhe had ratified her profeſſion after the deceaſe of her Husband, that ſhe ſhould be forced by Eccleſiaſtical cenſure to return into the Monaſtery, otherwiſe not, whereupon the ſaid <hi>Barnerdus</hi> makes this obſervation, <hi>votum timore mortis emiſſum non tenet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again this fear excuſeth a man as to gifts promiſes, or releaſe of actions by him made, in ſo much that if a man through fear gives, promiſeth or releaſes, he may recover forbear or repeat Eod. Cap. 2. again fear excuſeth from the obligation of an Oath for theſe are the words of <hi>Panorm. juramentum metu Preſtitum non eſt obligatorium, Cap. ſignificavit de eo qui duxit</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore a man is excuſed by fear a <hi>renuntiatione ſui juris,</hi> for whoſoever through fear renounceth a dignity or office, he may lawfully enter into it again notwithſtanding any ſuch <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation eod ad audaciam;</hi> and for that judged caſes in law are the beſt interpretations thereof, you may be pleaſed to take notice out of the Archives of the Regiſtry of <hi>Armagh,</hi> of what was decreed in the Church of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Droghedagh</hi> Anno 1553. by a provinciall Synode even in the time of <hi>George Dowdall</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Ardmagh</hi> and Primate of all <hi>Ireland</hi> concerning thoſe Prieſts and Prelats who had celebrated the Sacraments and other divine offices according to the rites of thoſe who were then deemed Hereticks, <hi>diffinitum eſt quod omnes ſupradicti qui non voluntate ſed metu hoc fecerunt admittentur ad gratiam &amp; abſolutionem vid Canonem</hi> 6. whence it appears that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34205:24"/>even Prieſts and Prelats may be excuſed by fear from ſuch acts as are deemed very great tranſgreſſions of law.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly to come directly to our caſe, If a man or woman contract marriage through fear they are excuſed a <hi>Contractu Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niali</hi> and are not thereby obliged.</p>
                  <p>The Canoniſts hold that there are three things conſiderable in marriage, <hi>ſides, proles, &amp; ſignificatio unionis inter Chriſtum &amp; eccleſiam,</hi> Fidelity, Iſſue, and the miſtical ſignification of union between Chriſt and his Church, now every one of theſe three are overthrown or moſt likely to be hindered by fear giving cauſe to a marriage, firſt the ſignification of the foreſaid Union is taken avvay by fear, for as Chriſt aſſumed human nature vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, ſo marriage which ſignifieth that Union, ought to be voluntary, and therefore void of fear, <hi>ut ſignum correſpondeat ſignato.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly fear is commonly an hinderance to iſſue in as much as that for the moſt part <hi>propter diſplicentiam ortam a timore non intendunt procreationi prolis</hi> as is obſerved by <hi>Antonius Genuenſis</hi> in his <hi>praxis Neopolitana p.</hi> 278.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly fear is repugnant to fidelity which is the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative from Adultery, for as the laſt Cited author writeth <hi>propter metum ſeu invitas nuptias de facili conguges labuntur in adulterium, nam quod quis non diligit facile contemnit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover that nothing may be wanting to way down the ballance on our ſide, I ſhall caſt in over and above the former reaſons and authorities, the expreſs opinions in point of ſuch other Lawyers, <hi>caſuist's</hi> and Schoolmen as will give a more pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous then needfull addition to what hath been ſaid, to prove that <hi>timor inique incuſſus</hi> is a <hi>diriment impediment</hi> to marriage, be pleaſed therefore to hearken unto <hi>Petrus Anchoranus</hi> in whoſe opinion you may ſafely fix your judgment <hi>extra de his quae vi metuſue cauſa fiunt. cap. abſolutionis, omnia geſta per me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34205:25"/>ſunt nulla,</hi> his reaſon is this <hi>quia metus continet in ſe dolum dolus autem dans cauſam contractui reddit eum nullum</hi> as you may ſee <hi>l. elegaenter ff. de do. ſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that <hi>Azpilcueta</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Caſuiſt concludes well <hi>p.</hi> 249. in theſe words, <hi>aunque los ſacramentos que imprimen character Comoil baptiſmo, valgan, peró il contrato del Matrimonio Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traydo per temor, no vale nada, proque anzi lo ordinò laygleſia per muchos reſpectos</hi> and a a little after he ſubjoyns as followeth <hi>el Miedo obra eſto no ſolamente, quando el Conſtrenido fingió Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentir y no conſentiò enel caſamiento, peró aun quando conſenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> verdaderamente,</hi> St. <hi>Thomas</hi> alſo is of this opinion, 4. <hi>diſt</hi> 19. I ſhall therefore Conclude with <hi>Malettus</hi> whoſe words are as pertinent in this behalf as his authority is Competent <hi>pte.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 586. <hi>Matrimonium metu cadente in conſtantem virum injuſte incuſſo contractum jure eccleſiaſtico irritum eſt,</hi> this concluſion is cleerly deduced from ſeveral places of the decretalls, <hi>ex ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite cum locum, ex cap: cum veniens ex cap. de Conſultatione de ſponſalibus,</hi> and herewith agree the moſt famous of the Schoolmen <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquin: in</hi> 4. <hi>diſt</hi> 19. <hi>quaeſtione unica Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo tertio, Banaventure</hi> on the ſame place <hi>Art unico</hi> q. 1. <hi>Richars dus Art:</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>Durandus</hi> q. 2. <hi>Paludamus</hi> q. 1. <hi>Art:</hi> 3. <hi>Major. q.</hi> 1. and the reaſon of this Concluſion is recited by <hi>Incognitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> on the ſentences <hi>lib</hi> 4. <hi>Dist:</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 31. out of the decretalls <hi>de ſponſalibus cap requiſivit,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>quia invitae nuptiae dificiles exitus habere Conſueverunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>ob:</hi> Perhaps it will be objected againſt us in extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the fear alleged and proved by us, that the Defendent and his Complices did not draw their Swords nor make uſe of their Piſtolls, to this I anſwer that the evidence given by us makes it apparent that they drew both their ſwords and Piſtolls but put the Caſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſince <hi>prejudicio veritatis</hi> that they had made no uſe of their ſwords nay that they had layd down their Arms
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34205:25"/>at her feet, let it be conſider'd what we finde written <hi>l. quoties</hi> Paragrapho <hi>qui in poteſtate &amp; l, in delictis in principio ff de noxa</hi> the words run thus, <hi>ibi ſufficit terror armorum ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videaniur deiceiſſe, idem dicendum eſt licet portans arma ea depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, cum enim poſſit ijs armis uti nihil corum depoſitio Confert.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ob.</hi> 2. It may peradventure be further objected, that it is not every fear that is a ſufficient impediment to Mariage, and this I grant to be true in ſeveral inſtances, as for example, if <hi>Meius</hi> be not <hi>incuſſus a cauſa libera ad exiorquendum conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> but a <hi>cauſa naturali intrinſica,</hi> for which ſeaſon a Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age Contracted by him whom the Phiſitian could he ſhould dye unleſs he did ſudenly marrie a Wife, is good and valid, becauſe the ſear that forced him upon marriage did ariſe from a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral intrinſick Cauſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Si juſté incutiatur metus a lege vel a Judice</hi> for <hi>capite ex literis, Extra, de ſtonſalibus</hi> we read <hi>ſi metus juſte incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatur a lege vel a Judice Praecipiente Matrimonium, tali metu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minime infirmatur matrimonium,</hi> and there is alſo the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>Si metus juslus incutiatur ab homine privato,</hi> for if a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall threaten the Raviſher of his Daughter to accuſe him Criminally upon the Statute of King <hi>James</hi> of force in this Kingdom, unleſs he take her to Wife, in this Caſe <hi>metus cenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur juſte incuſſus,</hi> and a marriage ſo Contracted and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate is firm enough though it proceeded from ſear of an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, but theſe caſes of <hi>Juſtus metus,</hi> and <hi>incuſſus a cauſa libera</hi> do not come within the State of our Controverſie, and therefore conclude nothing againſt us, nor do they require any further anſwer then that the fear raiſed in the minde of the Actrix was an unjuſt fear <hi>ex parte defendentis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ob,</hi> 3. It may be objected that weapons not drawn out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to uſe are not ſufficient to raiſe ſuch a fear as may <hi>cadere in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantem virum,</hi> for anſwer hereunto, it will be neceſſary firſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34205:26"/>of all to declare what manner of fear it is that may <hi>Cadere in fortem virum,</hi> which I ſhall do in the reſolution of <hi>Malettus, ad metum cadentew in fortem virum reducitur metus mortis vel mutilationis, vel fuſtigationis, atrocis cruciatus, vel incarcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, vel exilij vel ſervitutis, vel ſtupri, amiſſionis status honorifici, amiſſionis omnium bonorum vel magnae partis, vel rei pretioſae vel metus infamiae tam juris quam facti, Malettus par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. malleatione</hi> 56. <hi>bractea</hi> 44. <hi>p.</hi> 589. <hi>Col</hi> 1. but to give a more direct anſwer to the objection I ſhall betake my ſelf to the words of the Law <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>in principio, &amp; quia armatiff. de vi &amp; vi armata</hi> the words are theſe, <hi>metus armorum cadit in conſtantem virum, licet portans arma iis non matur,</hi> again a leſs fear then uſually falls <hi>in conſtantem virum</hi> would voyd the Marriage of my Client, by reaſon not only of the imbecillity of her Sex but alſo of the frailty of her tender years, the Law doth much indulge imbecillity and frailty for which reaſon women <hi>ob fragilitatem ſexus</hi> may notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their obligations to Creditors, plead the priviledge of the <hi>Vellejan Senatuſconſult</hi> for their immunity, as alſo <hi>minors ob im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becilitatem ingenij,</hi> if they become bound for the payment of debts may plead the advantage of the <hi>Macedonian Senatuſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult</hi> which ſets them free from any ſuch obligation, both theſe concurred in my Client <hi>fragilitas ſexus</hi> and <hi>imbecillitas ingenij</hi> at the time of her abduction ſhe was a Minor and under the age of Sixteen years, and therefore a leſs fear then what may <hi>Cadere in conſtantem virum</hi> is ſufficient, <hi>Autonius Genuenſis</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his opinion thus <hi>Minor metus excuſat magis mulierem quam maſculum quandoquidem fragilior eſtratione ſexus Cap. indignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> 32. q. 9. but <hi>Abbas in dicto Capite cum locum</hi> ſaith, <hi>ex parte mulieris requiritur metus qui cadere potest in conſtantem mulierem, &amp; Minor metus, quando concurrit in famina tenera aetas; cum concurrent duae qualitates, ſexus &amp; aetatis, vide praxin Curiae Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopalis Neopolitanae p.</hi> 278. <hi>Anno</hi> 3.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:34205:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ob.</hi> 4. It may alſo be objected that our former concluſion doth ſuppoſe a falſe foundation, and that there can be no ſuch <hi>metus</hi> or fear as may <hi>Cadere in fortem virum,</hi> for that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the third of his Ethicks Cap. 8. ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> i. e. <hi>fortioris eſſe in terroribus vacare terrore &amp; perturbatione,</hi> and if no fear or terrour can befall a valiant man, how can ſuch a pretenſion of fear be any impediment to marriage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To this objection, I ſhall anſwer firſt as a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, Secondly, as a Critick. my firſt anſwer is agreeable to the ancient Greek Scholias, and the latin Modern <hi>Comentaries viz,</hi> that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> did not hereby require that a conſtant or valiant man ſhould be totally exempt from fear, but that ſuch a perſon ſhould not fear any thing but what right reaſon ſhould dictate unto him as worthy of fear, nor in a higher degree then pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhould rate, now certain it is what Doctor <hi>Pariſienſis libro quarto</hi> ſaith <hi>dictat recta ratio plus debere timere mortem vel Carcerem quam actum Matrimonij alias diſplicentem,</hi> my ſecond anſwer ſhall conſiſt chiefly in the true recital of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> words in the Greek and a true tranſlation of them the Greek words therefore are theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>id eſt fortioris videtur eſſe in improviſis terroribus vacare terrore &amp; perturbatione quam in perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is,</hi> the words therefore as you may be pleaſed to obſerve in a true recital and a faithfull tranſlation, do not run by way of oppoſition abſolutely prohibiting all kinds of fear, but comparatively ſet forth that a valiant man is leſs to dread ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain and unexpected ſurprizes of fear, then apparent or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected dangers. I confeſs that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> rather may be wanting inſome Copies, yet the particle which cannot relate to any other word then <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or to one of the like import and would be infignificant if the other were not either expreſſed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34205:27"/>or implyed, juſtifies the copies where it is uſed to be moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and authentique, hence it followeth that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or if you will not allowe that word in the text, then the particle: is to be rendred rather <hi>per magis comparativum</hi> then by <hi>potius correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ivum,</hi> and not as it is taken <hi>Galatians</hi> 4.9. where <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>Magis hoc loco correctionem verius babet quam comparationem,</hi> the words there are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> nor, as it is rendred <hi>John</hi> the 3.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> men loved darkneſs more then light, that is they loved dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and not the light, not comparatively but oppoſitively, which ſence of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> though allowed by moſt other tranſlations, yet the <hi>Ethiopick</hi> interpreter renders it in a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative forme, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> yet ſo as the ſence is the ſame for the <hi>Ethiopick</hi> doth not render the words according to our Greek Copie, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>dilexerunt homines magis tenebras quam lucem,</hi> but thus <hi>dilexit Deus mundum &amp; elegit homo tenebras potius quam lucem</hi> for the words in the <hi>Ethiopick</hi> run thus <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and it is clear that though we may love one thing better then another comparatively, and ſo may love both together, yet we cannot chooſe after that manner but we muſt take the one and leave the other, but by the way to juſtifie the <hi>Ethiopick</hi> tranſlation it is moſt evident that Greek Authors do uſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for <hi>eligere</hi> as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> I chooſe this before that, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reads <hi>Appianus Alexandrinus de bellis civilibus</hi> will find that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> are of like ſignification where the words <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> are tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Malunt ſervire quam aequo cum caeteris jure vivere</hi> but let it be ſuppoſed that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, were wanting in all eopies of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> we know it is a rule frequently made
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34205:27"/>uſe off in the interpretation of Scripture, that <hi>poſitivus non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunquam comparative debet intelligi,</hi> as in the Goſpel of St. <hi>Mark Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 43. the Greek runs thus in the very ſame Idiom with <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> where though the litteral interlineary interprets <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the poſitive degree <hi>pulchrum</hi> yet the <hi>Perſian</hi> tranſlation ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it comparatively by a word of the ſame ſound and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification with our comparative better, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>melius tibi fuerit,</hi> and moſt other tranſlations render it comparatively the <hi>Armenian</hi> indeed tranſlates <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the poſitive de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree thus <hi>laitſe kets <hi>bonum erit tibi,</hi>
                     </hi> yet the adjunction of the particle <hi>kets</hi> makes up a comparative ſentence thus <hi>laitſe kets hel ikeanſn jaiptenits mtanel kan erchois tſern oinel erthal i chehen <hi>id eſt melius tibi fuerit mancum ingredi in vitam aeternam quam habere duas manus &amp; abire in Gehennam,</hi>
                     </hi> ſo that from what hath been principally ſaid in anſwer to this objection it followeth that the words of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> alledged againſt us are to be taken comparatively and not ſimply prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitively viz, not but that a valiant man may fear, but that he is to be leſs fearfull in a ſuddain and unexpected ſurprize, then in apparent and expected dangers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ob.</hi> 5. It may be further objected that though the <hi>metus</hi> or fear was a juſt <hi>incuſſus</hi> at firſt, yet it was not ſo all the time they were together, I ſhall with a ready anſwer unload the weight of this objection by offering unto your conſideration what is already proved viz, that ſhe was altogether under the power of the Defendent and his complices untill the 2d. February, when ſhe was reſcued from him in this City which in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of law continues the fear, for ſo ſaith <hi>Sanches lib.</hi> 4. <hi>diſp.</hi> 18. <hi>Anno</hi> 7. <hi>durat timoris cauſa dum durat ſubjectio timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem incutienti,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But perhaps if the Defendent were preſent he would as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34205:28"/>reply her unto, as he hath already falſly alledged elſe where that ſhe ſeemed by the indication of ſome exteriour acts at the time of her feigned or pretended marriage to be at liberty, to this I anſwer that ſhe was there ſo farr from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying her liberty, that it is apparent ſhe was under a great force, which I make good by the words of <hi>Zanches de matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio lib.</hi> 4. <hi>diſp.</hi> 18. <hi>Anno</hi> 9. which are theſe, <hi>ut autem actus exterior inducat metus purgationem cenſeatur<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſpontaneus deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur ut omni ex parte ſignificet liberam &amp; ſpontaneam voluntatem quia ſi ullam aliam interpretationem recipere poſſi non cenſelitur purgare metum,</hi> but put the caſe that as to all exteriour acts ſhe had ſeem'd to be at liberty, this had not been fufficient <hi>purgare metum</hi> ſo long as the firſt cauſe of fear continued, for thus ſaith <hi>Zanches lib.</hi> 4. <hi>diſp.</hi> 18. <hi>Anno</hi> 7 <hi>durante cauſa metus, durat metus quamvis in actu exteriori appareat ommmoda libertas, paria enim ſunt quod quis compellatur vel compella poſſit l. noviſſime ff. quod falſo tutore auctore geſium eſſe dicetur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Furthermore to ſhew you how little any indications of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent do ſignifie as to the purgeing of fear in a caſe of marriage, I ſhall collect into as contracted a brevity as I can, ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tions which I find in <hi>Earboza</hi> his <hi>vota deciſiva canonica, voto primo,</hi> delivered in a caſe of this nature debated and decided <hi>in curia Matritenſi</hi> between two noble perſonages viz, <hi>Ludovick</hi> and <hi>Joſepha</hi> which I ſhall apply in anſwer to this objection, the poſitions are theſe.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Metus antecedens nor purgatur per hilarem vultum tempore contracti Matrimonij extenſum. Anno.</hi> 104.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Riſus in actu Matrimonij contrahendi non eſt indicium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſus Anno</hi> 107.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Metus praeambulaus non purgatur ex cantu &amp; riſu puellae An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 127.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Metus non dicitur purgains ex oſculo &amp; refectione.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:34205:28"/>
                     <item>5. <hi>Per verba</hi> ſponte facio <hi>per metium paſſum tempore metus prolata, non purgatur metus, ſed geminatur, ibid. Anno</hi> 8.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Nay <hi>Alciat.</hi> goeth farther <hi>reſp.</hi> 5. <hi>idemeſt ſi matrimonio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracto ſubſequatur dotis inſtrumentum,</hi> but <hi>Abbas</hi> in <hi>capite ſuper hoc de renuntiatione</hi> giveth one reaſon which ſerves to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the truth of all the forementioned poſitions in theſe words, <hi>etianſi puella riſit dum deſponſaretur raptori eum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> oſcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſt, attamen ex quo durabat eadem metus cauſa, praeſumitur me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu conſenſiſſe, &amp; riſum illum finxiſſe, Bartholus</hi> alſo ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe <hi>l. penult ff. de condictione ob turpem &amp; injustam cauſam, &amp;</hi> in <hi>l.</hi> 2. (<hi>ob quod rieto cauſa.</hi> I conceive there hath been as much ſaid already as may ſerve to take off the force of the objection, yet to evict confeſſion from any ingenious adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, I will make uſe of ſome judgments in the caſe wherein lyes the ſinews of proof for <hi>res judicata pro veritate accipitur,</hi> in the moneth of <hi>June</hi> 1589. it being then debated in <hi>Rota Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana</hi> before the moſt illuſtrious <hi>Seraphino,</hi> whether conſent was given by the woman, to the man who claim'd her for his wife and urged in proof of a free conſent, that ſhe had paid and defraid the expences of them both for their dyet, and that ſhe had made ſeveral bargains, and had written ſeveral let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters unto him wherein ſhe expreſſed her ſelf to be his Wife, the judgment was, that <hi>nulla fuit habita ratio ejus quod uxor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciebat omnes expenſas victus tam pro ſe quam pro viro, nec quod fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerit varios contractus, &amp; ſcripſerit literas viro in quibus gerebat, ſe pro uxore, cum non eſſet conſtituta in plena libertate,</hi> this judg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment is related thus <hi>in praxi Curiae Archiepiſcopalis Neapolitana p.</hi> 282. where the Author ſaith further in theſe words, <hi>&amp; in eadem cauſa</hi> 23. Junij. 1589. <hi>coram Seraphino, ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> fuit habita ratio de muneribus Jocalium hinc inde tranſmiſſis propter radicem infect am metus precedentis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:34205:29"/>
                  <p>And whereas it hath been urged as a great indication of her fredom from feare that ſhe did declare her conſent to Mr Archdeacon <hi>Rouſe</hi> firſt I ſay there noe proof made of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent whatſoever expreſt by the actrix to the Archdeacon.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I ſhall ſhew how little ſuch a declaration of conſent doeth operate in the like caſe, from an Example which we finde in the practice of the Arch Biſhops Court in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples p.</hi> 282. <hi>die.</hi> 27. <hi>Ian:</hi> 1589. <hi>in eadem cauſa Coram Gipſio fuit, neque habendam eſſe rationem quod matrimonium ſuerit Contractum in facie eccleſiae ad interrogationem Archiepiſcopi, quafi quod me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus hoc pacto purgatus conſerctur,</hi> here the woman was married, not upon the interrogation of an Archdeacon, but an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, not in a privat Chamber guarded by the Complices of a Raviſher, but <hi>in facie eccleſiae,</hi> yet was it not thereby to be Concluded that ſhe gave a free conſent or that ſhe was void of fear for it was thus declared upon the heareing of the Cauſe, <hi>hoc locum ſibi vindicare, ſi dilucide oſtenderetur, puellam adeo in libertate tunc temporis Conſtitutam fuiſſe, ut de domo &amp; Civitate ex animi ſententia exire ac etiam a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fugere potuiſſet: vide praxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> curiae Archiepiſcopalis Neopolitanae p.</hi> 285. but ſure I am that the defendent will not <hi>dilucide oſtendere</hi> that the actrix was in ſo free a Condition in the Chamber where Mr <hi>Rouſe</hi> is ſaid to have interrogated her as that ſhe could have gone away from them <hi>in plenam libertatem,</hi> nor will be prove it <hi>uſque in Calendas Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas vel Idus Romanas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly I conclude with <hi>Baldus</hi> that noe <hi>ſpontaneuos</hi> act of the Actrix Could <hi>purgare metum unleſſe</hi> ſhe were <hi>Conſtituta in loco tuto ſi enim non ſit in loco tuto ſemper praeſumitur metus durare, Baldus de his quae vi metuſue cauſa fiunt</hi> if it ſhall be replyed that <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town</hi> was then reputed <hi>locus tutus,</hi> I anſwer that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may thinke it a place ſafe enough to ſecure to themſelves but whoſoever hath a ſoule able to ſet open the windows of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34205:29"/>ſence may eaſily perceive that it afforded her noe ſafety from them, for as <hi>Baldus</hi> ſaith, <hi>arctatus ſic quod non poſſit aufugere juſte timet, &amp; qui juſté timet non eſt in loco tuto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it ſhall be further objected that <hi>Matrimoninm Copula Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummatum</hi> may ſtand valid though fear was the cauſe thereof, I I ſhall allay the unreaſonableneſs of ſuch an objection with a double teſtimony to the contrary the one taken from <hi>Zanches</hi> the other from <hi>Reginaldns Zanches. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Diſ.</hi> 18. <hi>n.</hi> 5. <hi>non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum matrimonium ratum metu contractum, ſed etiam matrimonium Copula Conſummatum eſt invalidum. Reginaldus lib.</hi> 31 <hi>n.</hi> 19 <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pula enim nihil operatur ad validitatem matrimonij niſi adſit Con-Conſenſus validus &amp; liber.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it ſhall be rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yed that <hi>Oſtienſis</hi> and <hi>Didacus</hi> as alſo <hi>Paluda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in.</hi> 4. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 29 <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Art</hi> 4, as they are quoted by <hi>Marcus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius Genuenſis p.</hi> 281. hold, <hi>verum perfectumque eſſe matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium quando ſubſecuta eſt ipſius viri Carnalis Copula etiamſi metu &amp; vi Cognoviſſe mulierem alleget,</hi> I cannot deny the truth of thoſe words unleſs I ſhould prevaricat and deny my own knowledge, Nay I ſhall grant for <hi>corroboration</hi> of them that <hi>Menochius de preſumptionibus.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 27. ſaith <hi>hanc veriorem eſſe opinionem,</hi> Yet I ſhall not yeeld any thing of the cauſe, but give a ſatisfactory anſwer to what is alledged, firſt by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the true force of the words which import no more, then that a marriage may be held true and perfect being ſeconded by carnal knowledge, notwithſtanding the allegation of the man that he knew the woman, as being compelld by force and feare to act with her.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, By diſtinguiſhing between the Caſe of a man and woman, for as <hi>Monochius</hi> ſaith <hi>loco citato, in viro coeunte non poſſit metus aliquis conſiderari, quia ſi metus adeſſet, ceſſaret de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderium, ſine quo fruſtra adhibetur coreundi conatus,</hi> ſo that a man being according to the opinion of <hi>Menochius</hi> not ſubject
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34205:30"/>to ſuch compulſion, the allegation thereof, upon ſuch hype theſis will not ſerve his turne, yet a woman being ſubject to ſuch compulſion of Carnal knowledge as is Confeſt by ad La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiers, it may be alledged by her as an advantagious excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt a forced marriage though ſeconded with Carnall knowledge, the reaſon of the diference is, for that <hi>mulier in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vita &amp; coacta cognoſci poteſt, at vir invitus &amp; deſiderio carens nec erigere nec coire unquam poterit</hi> ſaith <hi>Marcus Antonius Genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis. p.</hi> 281.</p>
                  <p>But leaſt it may ſeeme to paſs away with a tacit allowance that he had Carnall knowledge of her after the ſaid pretended marriage, we deny that he was with her in <hi>carnis congreſſu</hi> after his comeing to Milltowne, but ſhould I grant that the Caſe were ſo, what advantage could the Defendent reape there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, for put the Caſe ſince <hi>prejudicio veaitatis</hi> that the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Defendent and his wicked Complices had prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo far with her as to perſwade her that the Marriage had been valid, whereas it was not, and that ſhe had thereupon volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily Conſented to a Maritall Copulation, the Marriage would not thereby have been ratified or Conſummate the reaſon is <hi>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> nihil magis conſenſui contrarium quam error Zanches. lib:</hi> 4. <hi>Diſp.</hi> 18. <hi>n.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ob.</hi> It may alſo be objected that regularly all things <hi>metu facta</hi> may be reputed valid vntill reſcinded by the action <hi>quod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vi metuſue cauſa</hi> or otherwiſe, and that therefore this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Marriage is to hold untill reſcinded by ſentence of this Court.</p>
                  <p>To ſhew the inſufficiency of this Argument I muſt diſtinguiſh, between the rule and the Caſe legally excepted from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehention of the rule, for <hi>non ex regula jus ſumatur ſed ex ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eſt quod regula fiat,</hi> neither is the rule compleat without the exceptions, whence the <hi>Logitians</hi> ſay <hi>anomalia addita analogiae
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34205:30"/>complet regulam perfectam,</hi> therefore I ſhall confeſs that there are ſome things <hi>metu facta</hi> which hold valid and are not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinded at all, inſomuch that the ordination of a Deacon or Prieſt <hi>metu facta</hi> is valid by the Cannon Law as to the Character though not <hi>quoad votum caſtitatis,</hi> and that there are other things <hi>metu facta</hi> which hold their force untill a legal hearing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciſſion, as for example, if <hi>Titius</hi> be forced by Compulſion to ſell his houſe and receive the money, the ſafe binds him untill he inſtitute his Action <hi>vi &amp; metus</hi> and obtaine reſciſſion thereof by Judgement of the Preſident of the Province <hi>Code de reſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda actione. l.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>Again a uſurious Contract confirm'd by oath may hold, nay cannot be reſcinded <hi>relaxatione Juramenti</hi> ſo ſaith <hi>Bertachinus Firmanus, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Contractus</hi> yet for all that which I have granted to fortifie the objection againſt me, I muſt ſay that <hi>matrimoninm metu habitum</hi> is invalid <hi>ab initio</hi> by diſpoſiton of Law and needs noe reſciſſion and thus much I am warranted to ſay by <hi>Navarr, de his qua vi metuſue Canſa fiunt, eonſil</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 6, <hi>&amp; per cap. cum locum extra de ſponſalibus, &amp; cap: ſignificavit de eo qui duxit in matrim</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The reaſon is, becauſe, where the ſubſtance of an Act which proceeds from fear Conſiſts in the liberty of the will there the Act is void <hi>ab initio,</hi> but ſo it is, that the ſubſtance of Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age abides in the liberty of the will as is confeſt by all Civilians Canoniſts and Caſuiſts who hold that <hi>nvptias non concubitus ſed conſenſus facit,</hi> wherefore ſaith <hi>Baldus ff quod metus eauſa l. ſi mulier. ſi dos &amp;c metus impedit omnem actum in quo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiritur voluntas ſpontanea, quia quando ſubſtantia actus eſt liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas volun tatis, actus metu factus eſt mullus ipſo jure, he adds aliter ſe res habet ſi non requiritur talis actus, nec requirit perciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>luntatem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it ſhall be demanded wherefore <hi>Matrimonium ex dolo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractum</hi> ſhould be more valid then <hi>Matrimonium metu contractum</hi>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:34205:31"/>I ſhall give noe further anſwer then to ſhew the diſſimilitude of both Caſes perfectly repreſented in the words of <hi>Baptiſta Zilet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tus, quia matrimonium non bonorum acceſſione ſed conſenſu per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>One difficulty more may be here interpoſed upon an inſtance from the Common Law of the Land which is this, if a man mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace me in my Goods, and that he will burn certaine eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of my land which he hath in his hand, if I will not make unto him a Bond, yet if I enter into a Bond by this terrour, I cannot avoid it by Plea, and the reaſon is ſaith the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour <hi>Bacon,</hi> becauſe the Law holdeth it an inconvenience to avoid a ſpecialty by ſuch matter of averrment, and therefore I am put to my Action againſt ſuch menaces; though I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Law to be as it is recited in this inſtance; yet I ſhall eaſily deliver my ſelf from that difficulty if it may be ſo called, by deſtinguiſhing between Menaces relating to ones Eſtate or his perſon, for the Law is much different in the Caſe of menaces to ones perſon, and therefore if I be reſtrained in my perſon as my Client was, or threatned with battery or the burning of my houſe which is a ſafety and protection to my Perſon, or with burning an Inſtrument of manumiſſion which is an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of my infranchiſiment, if upon ſuch menace or dureſs I make a deed I ſhall avoid it by Plea, and upon this diſtinction the Law varieth as you may ſee 13. <hi>H.</hi> 8.15. <hi>and</hi> 21. <hi>H.</hi> 7.28.</p>
                  <p>For if a treſpaſſer drive away my Beaſts over anothers ground, and I purſue to reſcue them, yet am I a Treſpaſſer to the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon whoſe ground I came; but if a man aſſaile my Perſon, and I fly over another mans ground then am I noe treſpaſſer. Againe if a Sherriff upon a <hi>Capias</hi> falſly return a <hi>Cepi Corpus &amp; quod eſt longuidus in priſona,</hi> there I may come in and falſifie the returne of the Sherriff to ſave my Impriſonment, for it is a <hi>Maxim</hi> of that Law that <hi>corporalis injuria non recipit eſtimatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem de futuro,</hi> yet I confeſs with Sir <hi>Frances Bacon</hi> in another
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34205:31"/>Caſe that if a Sherriff make a falſe return that I am ſummoned whereby I looſe my Land, yet becauſe of the inconvenience of drawing all things to incertainty and delay, if the Sherriffs returne ſhould not be Credited, I am excluded from any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment againſt it and am put to my action of deceipt againſt the Sherriff and the Summoners, and therefore it is ſaid upon the like ground that the Law in many Caſes which do concern Lands or Goods doth deprive a man of his preſent remedy and turneth him over to a further Circuit of remedie, rather then to ſuffer an inconvenience, but if it be a queſtion of perſonal pain or <hi>tort,</hi> the Law will not compell him to ſuſtain it and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect remedie, becauſe it holdeth noe damage a ſufficient recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for a wrong which is Corporal.</p>
                  <p>I having now broke thurrough thoſe objections which lay as it were in ambuſh to intercept me in my paſſage, I ſhall proceed further to evince from right reaſon and ſound Authority, that a Marriage Contracted by fear cannot be valid, nay that it is abſolutely void <hi>ab initio</hi> without reciſſion, and becauſe weake arguments do many times ſtiffen infidelty, I ſhall make uſe of none but what are drawn from the Chiefeſt inducements of beleefe.</p>
                  <p>Be pleaſed therefore to obſerve a Caſe Cleerly ſtated and determined in the very ſame words by <hi>Panormitan, Cap. Abbas de his quae vi metuſue Cauſa fiunt,</hi> where you may finde theſe words <hi>tenuit ſecundum matrimonium poſt primum meticuloſum, nulla prius petita reciſſione per actionem quod metus cauſa i. e.</hi> the ſecond Marriage was determined to ſtand good notwithſtanding a former marriage inforced by fear, not reſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by action, now if the firſt had been valid, the ſecond could never have been adjudged good, without reſciſſion of the former for <hi>Panormitan</hi> ſaith <hi>ſi valuiſſet primum matrimonium non tenuiſſet ſecundum, primo non annullato,</hi> the reaſon is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>matrimonium non poteſt conſiſtere inter duos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:34205:32"/>
                  <p>Again to argue with ampliation to a ſtronger caſe, if the Actrix had ratified ſuch pretended marriage brought on by force with her oath, it would not have been valid by law <hi>quiaper juramentum non ſuppletur defectus conſenſus</hi> and therefore the caſuiſt's ſay <hi>juramentum ſequitur naturam actus ſupra quam cadit, &amp; ſor titur conditiones illius,</hi> and therefore I conclude that as ſuch a marriage is invalid ſo alſo would the oath have been, and this is cleer <hi>ex capite qui duxit</hi> &amp;c. Where with agree <hi>Zanches, Roderigues</hi> and <hi>Malettas Malleatione</hi> 56 ſaying <hi>ideo opus non eſſe relaxatione juramenti quando ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonium per metum gravem celebratum fuit addito juramento, quia non opus eſt relaxatione ubi non eſt vinculum</hi> there being no need of relaxation, where there is no tye of obligation, ſo that I conclude with Doctor <hi>Pariſienſis, olim incognitus</hi> upon the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences that a marriage contracted by a forced conſent cannot be ratified by an oath, and that for this reaſon, viz, that by ſuch oath is ſworn <hi>aliquid praeteritum, aut aliquid praeſeus aut aliquid futurum,</hi> ſomewhat that is paſt, preſent or to come, firſt, if I ſwear what is paſt, it is moſt cleer, that my oath cannot ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie ſuch a marriage, for I either ſwear that I did lawfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and ſo I am perjured, and <hi>periurium non facit matrimonium,</hi> or I ſwear that I did not lawfully conſent, and then would it be leſs for the validateing of ſuch a marriage.</p>
                  <p>Secondly if the oath be <hi>de preſenti</hi> then I do either ſwear that I do inwardly from my heart yield a lawfull conſent, and then I am perjur'd, and by force of perury a marriage cannot be made good, or I ſwear that I do not lawfully conſent, and then it is much more invalid.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, If the oath be <hi>de futuro,</hi> as for example I ſwear that I will conſent unto thee, it is moſt certainly true that a marriage cannot be contracted by any ſuch conſent, becauſe it requires <hi>conſenſum de praeſenti verbis vel ſignis expreſſu,</hi> as you
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34205:32"/>may ſee <hi>extra de ſponſnlibus cap. cum locum, &amp; capite tua nos,</hi> ſince therefore every oath muſt be <hi>de praeterito, aut de preſenti aut de futuro,</hi> and none of theſe can ratifie a marriage contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by fear, it follows therefore that the pretended marriage being already proved invalid by reaſon of fear, cannot be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by oath:</p>
                  <p>I need argue no more the invalidity of the pretended mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage from the impediment of fear; or <hi>ratione timoris incuſſi,</hi> I ſhall therefore proceed <hi>ad impedimentum vis illatae,</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Duarenus l.</hi> 2. <hi>de eo quod metus Cauſa,</hi> is defined <hi>impetus qui repelli non poteſt,</hi> and is ſo odious in the Eye of the Civil and Cannon Law, that as all kinde of force is thereby prohibited, ſo alſo is there a moſt apt remedy and proviſion made for every kinde of force, and ſo ſaith <hi>Iohannes Eduenſis, neque enim vim aliquam poſſumus inferre proximo, quin ei fit aliquo juris remedio ſuccurſum,</hi> and there is great reaſon for it, for <hi>violentiam Coercere eſt legi opem ferre, cap: ſicut, extra de exceſſu prelatorum</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>vis</hi> or force is divided into theſe ſeveral kindes <hi>viz: vis inquieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, vis turbatiua, vis expulſiua, vis Cumpulſiua</hi> For that which is called <hi>vis inquietativa</hi> you have the remedy of the Interdict <hi>quod vi &amp; Clam, in. l</hi> 1. <hi>de vi &amp; clam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you be infeſted with the ſecond kinde of force which is <hi>vis turbativa,</hi> if it be in immoveables the Law affords you the interdict <hi>uti poſſidetis,</hi> if in goods moveable you may have the interdict called <hi>Interdictum utrobi</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you ſuffer a diſſeiſon, or diſpoſeſſion by the third kind of force which is tearmed <hi>vis expulſiua</hi> you may have for your immoveables the interdict <hi>unde vi</hi> and for your moveables the interdict <hi>vi bonorum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly if you ſuffer under a compulſive force which is our Caſe, you properly have the remeady of the action Called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34205:33"/>quod metus cauſa</hi> as you may ſee in the Code and <hi>ff.</hi> under that title, I having defined force in general and divided it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its ſeveral kindes, I ſhall now apply my ſelf to the laſt, which is <hi>vis compulſiua,</hi> and ſhew what influence it may have on our Caſe which conſiſts of a Rape and other violence offered or attempted by the Defendent to inforce her to marry with him, but firſt of all I hould my ſelf obliged to deſcribe the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Rape, and how repugnant it is to the Law, as to the nature of it <hi>tria requiruntur ad raptum proprie, nimirum vit il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata, abductio, &amp; ut fiat cauſa concubitus, vel alterius libidinis,</hi> Abduction is Cleerly proved, the <hi>vis illata</hi> is apparent in her unwillsngneſs and reſiſtance to be abducted, and their violent Carrying her away, and that it was <hi>concubitus cauſa</hi> appeares by the ſadneſs of the event.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If there had been noe conſtraint upon her, and that ſhe had gon away with him ſpontaneouſly without the knowledge of her Father it had not been a Rape but <hi>fuga voluntaria</hi> for ſaith <hi>Candidus, requiritur ad raptum ut vis inferatur ipſi vel hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſaltem ad quos pertinet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly. Had ſhe been removed by force from one Roome of an houſe to another onely <hi>commodioris concubitus gratia</hi> it had been noe Rape, for he that forceth a woman to ſuccumb to his luſt whom he findes her in a certaine place without abducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to another place of ſome diſtance doeth not properly commit a Rape.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly. If ſhe be not carryed away libidinis <hi>cauſa ſed redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendi in ſervitutem,</hi> it is no Rape but <hi>plagium,</hi> or as they ſay <hi>furtum hominis,</hi> yet it is not requiſite to a Rape that there ſhould be <hi>actualis concubitus,</hi> but it is ſufficient <hi>ut eo fine fiat,</hi> for ſaith <hi>Altiſiodorenſis, voluntas progreſſiua in actum pro facto reputatur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So much may ſerve to deſcribe the nature of a Rape, I am now to ſhew its repugnancy to Law, The Law of God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34205:33"/>it under the penalty of death to be inflicted on the Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Deutoronomie</hi> the 22. where it is ſaid in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>and if he lay hold on her he ſhall dye,</hi> the words ſeem at firſt to be very ſtrict <hi>viz.</hi> that whoſoever ſhall lay hold on a woman ſhall dye, therefore it will not be amiſs perhaps to explicat the words <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> by the ſeverall anoient and authentique tranſlations of the Bible, the ſeptuagint renders it by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, inforcing her, the <hi>Syriack</hi> hath it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and ſhall apprehend or hold her by force, the Caldy paraphraſe of <hi>Onkelos</hi> expounds it by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which though tranſlated in the Biblia <hi>Polyglotta apprehenderit</hi> cleerly ſignifies to prevaile by force or violence as in a Conflict, and ſo the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Interpreter hath expreſt it in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; and though the Interpreter of the <hi>Arabick</hi> tranſlation agrees with the vu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gar Latin <hi>apprehends</hi> yet the <hi>Arabick</hi> word in that place is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp; coercuerit eam</hi> which ſenſe it beares in <hi>Raphalengius Golius</hi> and <hi>Gigaeus,</hi> and indeed the very ſame <hi>Hebrew</hi> word <hi>Fxodus</hi> the 9. and the 2. is taken for a violent detention and is by <hi>Buxtorfius</hi> Tranſlated <hi>vi deti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens,</hi> and noe wonder, for that <hi>Abenezra</hi> the <hi>Rabin</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> thus <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> that is to ſay <hi>by holding them forcibly by the hand or ſome other member, as if one ſhould hold a dogg by the ears, Rabbi Solomon Iarchy</hi> alſo gives the like expoſition of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> theſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> I ſhall not render the words too familiar in the vulgar Engliſh, yet take them in as modeſt tearms as I can expreſs them in latin, <hi>ideſt apprehendens eum quaſi per pudenda vi detineret eum,</hi> ſo much (as you may be pleaſed to obſerve) an addition to the rigour of the word by a true tranſlation, takes by an equitable abatement from the ſeeming ſeverity of the Law, and indeed it might have been ſuppoſed too rigorous a Law, that a man
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34205:34"/>might not have ſo much as toucht any any woman without un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing ſo great a penalty as death. But perhaps on the other ſide it might be thought a very remiſs law that a Raviſher ſhould go unpuniſht or at moſt be puniſht only with that which is incident naturally to all men, even to the moſt innocent, which is death, for the whole penalty here expreſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp; morietur</hi> he ſhall dye, and ſo it is in our Engliſh tranſlation, but the <hi>Greek</hi> hath it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ye ſhall put him to death, the <hi>Syriack</hi> alſo renders it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> he ſhall be ſlain or put to death, ſo alſo the Chaldy paraphraſe and both the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may be taken as an overſight in ſome of thoſe worthy and learned perſons who were the publiſhers of the polyglott Bibles to render it by the word <hi>morietur,</hi> for it is better expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of the <hi>Arabick</hi> Interpreter <hi>interficietur,</hi> for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the <hi>Italian,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh, French,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> ought to be corrected as well as our Engliſh tranſlation, all which follow the vulgar latin <hi>morietur,</hi> from this penalty and the Criticall <hi>Guſto</hi> that I have given you the true ſenſe of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> you may clearly perceive that by the Judaick law there could be no marriage between the <hi>Raptor</hi> and the <hi>Rapta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall in the next place inſtanceint he Law of the twelve Tables, where I finde onely a plain prohibition without any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty ſubjoyned, for <hi>vim ingenuae feminae inferre caveto</hi> is all that I can obſerve mentioned in the remains of that Law Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Rape.</p>
                  <p>But the ancient Rom in Laws afterward ſharpned their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity not onely againſt the Raptors, but alſo all acceſſories to that Crime, inſomuch that they are brought under the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of this Conſtitution, <hi>viz. Conſcij veró aut Miniſtri raptus paenae capitali ſubjiciuntur, ſive nolentibus ſive volentibus virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus hoc egerint, parentibus ſi patientiam praebuerint, ac do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorem compreſſerint, deportatione plectendis, ſed &amp; ſi quis inter
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34205:34"/>haec Ministeria ſervilis conditionis fuerit compr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>henſus, entra ſexus diſtinctionem concremetur. vide Arnoldum de Herbolt de actionibus</hi> p. 642. and the <hi>Code de rapiu virginis l.</hi> 1. this law as you may obſerve by the by concludes worſe againſt the treacherous maid of the Actrix, then the figure <hi>Bocardo</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe yet deſervedly remaines.</p>
                  <p>Nay the Canon Law puniſheth not onely Servants but alſo all others, who are any way acceſſary to a rape with Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>infamy, incapacity</hi> for dignities and offices, as appeares by the Teſtimony of <hi>Gaſpar Aſtete, libro ſegundo del eſtado de las Lonzellas,</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>el raptor y los que le dieron favore, ſon deſcomulgados infames e incapaces de todas dignitades.</hi> Which is the reaſon that by the Lawes of Heraldry whoſoever he be who raviſheth a virgin, muſt bear his Eſcucheon reverſed, and it appeares further by a reſcript of the <hi>Concilium Aurelian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,</hi> which was Celebrated in the time of <hi>Pope Hormiſda,</hi> that the Church would not allow Sanctuary to Raviſhers.</p>
                  <p>My next inſtance ſhall be in the Law of the <hi>Saxons, l.</hi> 49. about the year of our Lord 1032. where it is ſaid in theſe words <hi>gif haw wudewan nyde name gebete wt bewere, gif haw meden nyde name gebete wet bewere i. e. qui viduam per vim ſtuprarit, proprij Capitis eſtimatione com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſato,</hi> nec <hi>mitiori Conditione ſit qui virgini vim intulerit,</hi> by this law alſo of the Saxons, you ſee there could be no marriage between the <hi>Raptor</hi> and the <hi>Rapta</hi> for <hi>gebete wet bewere</hi> he muſt looſe his life,</p>
                  <p>I might alſo give inſtance of the ancient Lawes of <hi>Ireland</hi> in force about the ſame time under the Government of <hi>Brian Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haim,</hi> what the penalty of a rape was then in this Kingdom by that Law, I cannot yet directly finde out, but the effect thereof ſhews that the Law againſt Rape was moſt ſtrict in it ſelf, &amp; as ſeverely executed, for the <hi>Annaliſts</hi> ſay that in the reign of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34205:35"/>this <hi>Monarch</hi> a ſingle woman might have travailed from <hi>Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us thuaid</hi> to <hi>Thuinchliodna</hi> being the whole length of <hi>Ireland</hi> and not meet one that would attempt to Raviſh her.</p>
                  <p>Again what was the nature of this offence at the Common Law and what acts of Parliament have been enacted in Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thereof I need not ſet forth at large, for it clearly appears in my Lord Cooke the third of the Inſtitutes, <hi>Cap.</hi> 12. who there referrs you to a large Margin with a long and numerous traine of Ancient and Authentique<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quotations, he there alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly recites Caſes out of the Parliament Rolls, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> to prove, in how great deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this offence was held in Ancient times and parilcularly in the Caſes of <hi>Iſabell</hi> the wife of <hi>Iohn Botiler:</hi> and of <hi>Margaret</hi> ſometime wife of Sr: <hi>Thomas Malefait.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to be more particular, Rape is Felony by the Common Law, according to to the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the 2.34. and by the thirteenth of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, the Raviſher ſhall have judgment of Life and member.</p>
                  <p>Nay this offence by the Statute Lavv is ampliated ſo far as to become felony in the ayders and abettors as we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, nay ſo far is it extended in the vvords of the Lord Cook as to bring acceſſories aide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and abetters under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of principalis, for theſe are the vvords in the 3. of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes <hi>cap.</hi> 10. if any be preſent, abetting and aiding any to do the act, though the offen"illegible"e be perſonal and to be done by one onely, as to Commit Rape, not onely he that doeth the Act is a principall, but alſo they that be preſent abetting and aiding the miſdoer, are principal alſo, for proof hereof I recommend to your Conſideration 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Anno primo Ed.</hi> 4. and ſhall further put you in minde that by the 11.12. and 13. <hi>Jacobi cap.</hi> 3. Clergie is taken avvay in Caſe of Rape.</p>
                  <p>I have novv ſhevved you the nature of a Rape and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnancie
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34205:35"/>thereof to the Lavv of God, the Lavv [of the tvvelue Tables the Elder <hi>Roman</hi> Lavvs, the Ancient <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Lavves before the Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to the Common Lavv, as alſo to the Ancient and recent Statute Lavves.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall novv dravv near to thoſe Lavves vvhich are of moſt Concernment, to ſhevv that there could be no Mrrriage lavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Contracted betvveen the Actrix and Defendent by reaſon of the ſaid Rape and the force that vvas upon her dureing the time limited in the State of the Caſe, vvhich vvas from the firſt inſtant of her abduction untill her reſtitution to liberty.</p>
                  <p>To this effect I ſhall make uſe onely of the Civil Lavv and Canon Lavv, and the Doctrine of the beſt and moſt renovvn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Caſuiſts as being the beſt rules by vvhich things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can be vvarrantably determined, and though thoſe reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht treaſuries might afford me abundant authorities and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, proportionable to the Offerings made for the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle more then ſufficient, I have made choiſe of a fevv, yet ſuch as vvill ſtifly beare up the vvaight of the Cauſe, and I ſhall take my riſe from the Code. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de raptu virginum</hi> (<hi>l.</hi> 1.) vvhich book hath as much reaſon to perſvvade as authoritie to oblige where it is of force, the vvords are theſe <hi>raptores virginum honeſtarum vel ingenuarum quaſi peſſima crimina peccantes, capitis ſupplicio plectendos diſcernimus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the next place be pleaſed to conſult the <hi>Authentiques col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione</hi> 9. <hi>tit.</hi> 25. <hi>novella</hi> 43. <hi>de raptis mulieribus</hi> where it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in theſe words, <hi>matrimonium inter raptorem &amp; raptam non tenet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If there were need of a more inlarged authority with a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther addition of reaſon you might reſort to <hi>Simon a Gronwegen vander made. cod de raptu virginum</hi> (<hi>l.</hi> 1.) <hi>ſi vis publica raptum comitetur aliaeve circumſtantiae crimen aggravent.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34205:36"/>facinoris atrocitas publicam vindictam poſcit, quae per ſubſequeus matrimonium nequaquam tolli poteſi aut aboleri,</hi> the reaſon which he gives is moſt prevalent, for it is no leſs then an undoubted rule of Law, <hi>viz: privatorum Conventio juri publico derogare non debet.</hi> There is an illuſtrious Example hereof in the regiſtry of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> in the Caſe of <hi>Carolus Audax,</hi> which directly ſutes with thelaſt recited authority.</p>
                  <p>If what hath been alledged out of the Civil Law hath not furniſht you with inducements, motives and arguments ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to decree, that there was not nor could be any marriage lawfully or validly Contracted, between them dureing the time of the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, you may be pleaſed to conſider fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vvhat I ſhall preſent unto you taken out of the text of the Canon Lavv, 36. <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. are theſe vvords repleat vvith authority in the point, <hi>raptor in uxorem non poteſt raptam accipere;</hi> but the reaſon ſubjoyned is yet more bigg vvith emphaſis. <hi>Quia eorum coniunctio auctoritate canonum ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum penitus prohibetur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again <hi>Extra</hi> 36. <hi>q</hi> 2. <hi>cap. placuit</hi> you have vvords of no leſs import then the former allegation, <hi>placuit ut hi qui rapiunt fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minas, eas nullatenus habeant uxores, quamvis eis poſtmodum Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, aut eas dotaverint, vel nuptialiter eum Conſenſu parentum acceperint.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The councell of <hi>Aquiſgrane</hi> alſo did not only ſeparate ſuch mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, <hi rend="margQuotes">but would not allow that ever after they ſhould be man and wife as we find in <hi>Eurchard,</hi> and the ſame was veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Councel of <hi>Melda</hi> which for its warrant quotes a Synodall <hi>definition</hi> of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> to the ſame purpoſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence it was that <hi>Vrban</hi> the 8th of later times ordered <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione ſexta, Regula Concellariae</hi> 49. that in all diſpenſations <hi>ſuper aliquo gradu Conſanguinitatis vel affinitatis ponatur Clauſula, ſi mulier rapta non fuerit,</hi> though it was obſerved in reſcripts
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:34205:36"/>of that nature long before in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in the Caſe of <hi>Nicholas Dowdall</hi> and <hi>Ellen Dilane</hi> of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Armagh</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Phillip</hi> and <hi>Mary;</hi> for it appears in the Black book of <hi>Armagh fol.</hi> 20, by a reſcript from Cardinal <hi>Poole</hi> to diſpenſe with them in a then prohibited degree of conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity, he there inſerts this Clauſe in his letters to the then Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh</hi> to abſolve and diſpenſe with them, <hi>dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo dicta mulier propter hoc ab aliquo rapta non fuerit,</hi> I finde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the like Clauſe in another reſcript of the ſame Cardinal, in the behalf of one <hi>Richard Bedlewe</hi> and <hi>Matilda Bathe.</hi> The Civil and Canon Law being ſo expreſs in the Caſe as I have already rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it were needleſs to offer any thing further of authority, yet to ſhew the Conſent of other approved Authors, be pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a word or two to hear the opinion of the Caſuiſts to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy you as well in point of Conſcience as Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Emanuell Sa &amp; Diana tractatu de Sacramentis p.</hi> 152. <hi>reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi> 261. ſaye <hi>inter Raptorem &amp; Raptam non poteſt fieri validum matrimonium, quamdiu eſt in poteſtate Raptoris,</hi> and ſo the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Cardinals have often declared ſaith <hi>Diana.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Herewith alſo agrees <hi>Rodrigues Luſitano cap. de matrimonio p.</hi> 641. <hi>non vale el matrimonio entre el que arrebata y la areba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tada mientras ella eſta en ſu poder,</hi> furthermore. <hi>Carolus Mallettus Malleatione</hi> 57. <hi>Bractea</hi> 14. <hi>p.</hi> 605. tells us that <hi>matrimonium Contractum inter Raptorem &amp; Raptam dum ſub poteſtate Raptoris exiſtit eſt proſſus irritum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We have now proved by Authority of Law and conſent of Caſuiſts, that there could be no valid marriage between the Actrix and the Defendent: <hi>ratione metus incuſſi &amp; vis illatae,</hi> and particularly <hi>ratione raptus</hi> dureing the time which paſſed between the abduction and reſtitution to liberty. This done, I ſhould immediatly proceed to declare his puniſhment, for his falſe and Calumnious jactitation of Marriage with the Actrix, but
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34205:37"/>that I am neceſſitated to break through the ambuſh of ſome few doubts which lye in the way. The firſt is a ſuppoſal that the Actrix had given her conſent to what was done, I anſwer, that the Raptor can never be admitted to the proof of ſuch an allegation, but for better aſſurance of what I ſay, take the words of <hi>Pacianus de probationibus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 50. <hi>n.</hi> 30. <hi>p.</hi> 262. <hi>Raptor nou auditur probare volens puellam raptam ſpoute ſibi Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſiſſe quando puella probavit violentiam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer further, that were he admitted to ſuch proof, nay could he make good proof thereof, it would not availe him in that behalf, for ſaith <hi>Navarr Conſilio</hi> 2. <hi>de raptoribus</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 319.) decideing the Caſe between <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Brancaleona</hi> on the one part, and the Father of <hi>Brancaleona</hi> of the other, <hi>conſenſus puellae ut raperetur, non ſufficit. ut non dicatur rapta, quia ut dicatur talis ſufficit ut contra voluntatem patris ſit abſtracta, ſiue id fiat de voluntate puelle ſiue Contra voluntatem ejus</hi> and the Doctrine of <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> 2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 154. <hi>Art.</hi> 7. juſtifieth this deciſion, you have alſo the ſame Caſe and the like deciſion together in <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Azpilcueta titulo de raptoribus</hi> in theſe words <hi>Iohannes ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puit Brancaleonam patri, ipſa tamen volente &amp; conſentiente cum qua contraxit matrimonium, poſtmodum mota lite a patre, fuit lata ſententia contra dictos Iohannem &amp; Brachaleonam</hi> it is alſo ſaid there that <hi>rapiens non poteſt raptam ducere in uxorem niſi poſt quam ſeparata fuit ab illo.</hi> It will be objected perhaps that the arguments which we offered in proof of her diſſent and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the pretended marriage <hi>viz.</hi> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> weeping and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are but fallible and might have been feigned, for we read in the ancient Annals of <hi>Ireland</hi> that <hi>Dearberguill</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Malaughlin</hi> King of <hi>Meath,</hi> and not his wife as <hi>Cambrenſis</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke it,) being for a long time enamour'd with <hi>Dermott Mac Murrough</hi> then King of <hi>Leinſter,</hi> ſhe ſent him word by a privat meſſenger, that her husband King <hi>Tighearnan</hi> was then gon a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34205:37"/>Pilgrimage to St: <hi>Patricks</hi> Purgatorie, and that ſhe deſired him without any delay to come for her promiſeing to become his wife, it appears alſo in the ſame Story that <hi>Dermott Mac Murrough</hi> did imbrace the motion and tooke hold of the opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity which the abſence of her huſband gave him, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding her amours, her invitation of him and promiſes to come away with him without oppoſition, when he came for her ſhe put on a ſeeming unwillingneſs, and to give the better Colour to her diſſimulation, ſhe ſtruggled wept and cryed, as though ſhe had never Conſented to have Eloped with him; but that he had violently forced her away againſt her will and minde, ſo that the ſtruggling weeping and crying of women are not alwaies certaine indications of their minde.</p>
                  <p>My anſwer to this objection ſhall be to ſhew the diſſimilitude of both Caſes, for in the Caſe of my Client, it is not ſo much as alledged, that ſhe gave any incouragement unto, or was privie to the intention of the Defendent to take her away, Secondly, my Client afterwards made a proteſtation againſt the abductor, which the King of <hi>Meath</hi>'s Daughter did not; if therefore that Queen had not invited <hi>Dermott Mac Murrough</hi> to that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, or had ſhe proteſted in forme of Law as my Client did, againſt it, her ſtruggling weeping and crying might have been preſumed to have been as unfeigned ſymptoms as my Clients were real arguments of her diſſent.</p>
                  <p>If it ſhould be alledged on the behalf of the Defendent that there is no full proof that he had Carnal knowledge of her, and that therefore the pretended Marriage doeth not appeare to be void <hi>ratione raptus</hi> to this objection I ſhould make three anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, the firſt is that we have ſufficiently proved the violent Compreſſion of her, the 2. is that in caſe we had no direct proof thereof <hi>Fontanella</hi> ſaith, upon a general preſumption of Law, <hi>rapta mulier vix a nullo creditur unquam integra exiiſſe a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34205:38"/>manu raptoris Clauſula</hi> 5. where he inſtanceth <hi>de Helena &amp; rapin ejus a Theſeo,</hi> My third anſwer is, that Carnal knowledge is not neceſſary to the Conſummation of a Rape, for it may be <hi>non intercedente Copula</hi> and therefore <hi>Carolus Mallettus</hi> ſaith <hi>delictum raptus in ipſa abductione conſummatur, Malleatione.</hi> 57. <hi>p.</hi> 605. all which agrees with what I alleadged before out of <hi>Altiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorenſis,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it ſhould be objected that <hi>Paulus</hi> that ancient and moſt learned Lawyer <hi>lib</hi> 2. <hi>ſententiarum tit.</hi> 19. inſtanceth of ſome Marriages in caſe of Rape and thereupon ſaith <hi>matrimonia haec jure non contrahi, ſed tamen contracta non ſolvi, i. e.</hi> ſuch Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages ought not to have been made, but being made they cannot be diſſolved, for anſwer hereunto, I muſt diſtinguiſh <hi>inter legem perfectam &amp; imperfectam.</hi> The imperfect Law is that which does not indeed reſcind the fact done contrary to its prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but inflicts a puniſhment upon the tranſgreſſour, ſuch as was the <hi>lex furia teſtamentoria,</hi> and ſuch as is the Law concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forbidden Marriages againſt the Fathers will which are thoſe mentioned by <hi>Paulus</hi> the Lawyer, and which by the Civil Law comes under the notion of a rape, now in this Caſe of Marrying without conſent of the Father the Marriage muſt ſtand, and the Married muſt abide the puniſhment, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing notwithſtanding in the valuation of the Civil Law reckned as Concubines, and their Children Baſtards, and there was neither Dowrie nor Marriage Portion allowed, ſo that though ſuch Marriage was civilly null and made uncapable by that law of Civil benefits and advantages; yet it vvas not made naturally <hi>null,</hi> and <hi>Paulus</hi> gives an excellent reaſon for it in theſe vvords, <hi>contemplationem enim publicae utilitatis pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatorum commodis anteferri,</hi> for it is of publique Concern that marriages naturally valid be not reſcinded, but it is of privat Commoditie and emolument that the Father ſhould
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34205:38"/>be pleaſed in the choyſe of his Son in Lavv, but the inſtance out of <hi>Paulus</hi> concerns onely a marriage without the Fathers conſent, but not againſt the conſent of the raviſht Party, for ſuch Marriage as I have already proved, comes under the other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Diſtinction <hi>viz. lex perfecta,</hi> which either in its ſelf or at leaſt by the miniſtry of the Magiſtrat, reſcinds whatever was done againſt her preſcript, and herewith agrees the Law <hi>non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium</hi> C. de <hi>legibus,</hi> where it is ſaid <hi>nullum Contractum, inter eos videri volumus ſubſecutum, qui contrahunt, lege Contrahere prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bente,</hi> and furthermore the ſame Law denounceth <hi>ea quae lege fieri prohibentur, ſi fuerint facta, non ſolum inutilia ſed pro infectis etiam habeantur,</hi> me thinks that Doctor <hi>French</hi> who hath ſpoken ſo much formerly ſhould now, rather then ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, deſire the benefit of <hi>pro infectis habeantur</hi> which I ſhall allow him in as large a manner as the gloſs will afford, which ſaith, <hi>maleficia contra legem faecta, haberi pro factis ad incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum facientis, ſed pro infectis ad commodum injuriam paſſae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It may perhaps be objected further, that the Actrix hath loſt the benefit of reclamation, for ſhe ought to have commenced her ſuit immediatly <hi>data oportunitate recedendi,</hi> for <hi>qui vult ſe liberare ratione metus ab aliquo vinculo debet illo ceſſante ſtatim reclamare</hi> according to that old and celebrated diſtich in the gloſſe,
<q>
                        <l>Effuge Cum poteris ne conſenſiſſe puteris</l>
                        <l>Nam ſi perſtiteris illius uxor eris.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this objection the main force whereof (if any there be) lyeth in the words <hi>ſtatim reclamare,</hi> I anſwer thus, that the word <hi>ſtatim,</hi> though it be alwayes Confined to a ſhort time, it doth not every where import an inſtant but admits of <hi>aliquod temporis interval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34205:39"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:34205:39"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:34205:40"/>&amp; tempormentum, ff de ſoluto matrimonio, l quod decimus. lib:</hi> 24. <hi>tit.</hi> 3. <hi>infor:</hi>) ſo that <hi>Lucas de Penna,</hi> on the Code <hi>de erogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one militaris annonae. l.</hi> 5. (<hi>lib:</hi> 12. <hi>tit.</hi> 37. ſaith that the word <hi>ſtatim</hi> is ſometimes extended <hi>adunum</hi> ſometimes <hi>ad duos menſes,</hi> within which time our ſuit was Comenced.</p>
                  <p>I confeſs that <hi>Skene</hi> in his expoſition on that part of the Laws of <hi>Scotland</hi> which they call <hi>Regiam Majeſtatem,</hi> expoſeth himſelf in theſe very words that the Complaint of a Rape ſhould be made the ſame day and night in the quilk the Crime is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>quia lapſu diei hoc crimen perſcribitur, Skene de verbo Rape</hi> and hence it is I believe that <hi>Spellman</hi> ſpeaking of the Conſuetudes or Statutes of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſaith <hi>ſi ultra unam noctem expectaverit rapta ad habendum concilium amicorum ſuorum ita quod recenter non faciat ſequelam, &amp; hoc probetur, Defendens id eſt Rapior quietus erit,</hi> I think we are more concern'd in the opinion of <hi>Fleta. lib.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; praeterea</hi> whoſe opinion it is, that <hi>conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri oportet foeminam cui illata eſt vis intra quadraginta dies,</hi> which termination of time as a good Antiquarie obſerves vvas derived from the Salique Lavv.</p>
                  <p>But to make a more direct anſvver to theſe tvvo inſtances, as for the Conſtitutions of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they have no bindeing force on us, vvho are govern'd by Lavvs of our ovvn, and as for that of <hi>Fleta,</hi> I think it is not applicable to our Caſe, but to an appeale of Rape at the Common Lavv, according to the firſt of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the firſt and the 13. and the 3. <hi>Edward</hi> 1. vvhere vve read that any perſon may ſue vvithin 40. dayes, but if not then, the King ſhall have Suit, furthermore the time of ſuch appeal hath been inlarged in after times as appears by <hi>Stampford</hi> in the Pleas of the Crovvn, ſpeaking of a ſhorter time antiently limited for proſecution of an appeal at the Common Lavv, vvho vvrites after this manner, <hi>tamen le ley nest iſſint priſa ceſt jour car ſi homme fait freſh ſuit, Comeni que il ne Comenſa ſon apel. deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34205:40"/>tres Ans apres uncore ſera dit aſſes bon. i. e.</hi> The Lavv is not ſo taken at this time for if freſh ſuit be made, although an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal be not Commenced within two or three years, it ſhall be good enough, wherefore to compare this caſe with ours, we ſay that ſhe did not only Commence her ſuit ſo ſoon as ſhe recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de her ſelfe out of the amazment that this force brought upon her which could not have been done ſooner; but alſo immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly on the firſt night ſhe came to <hi>Dublin,</hi> ſhe made a proteſt in due forme of Law whereby ſhe perpetuated her right both of action and exception, for annulling the Marriage for want of Conſent which is apparent in the remarque of <hi>Antonius Genuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis p.</hi> 282. for there he ſaith <hi>Notandum praeterea proteſtationem puellae, multum removere Conſenſum, non obſtante quod ſit Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria facto, cum proteſtatio in his quae dependent a voluntate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra, removeat Conſenſum ab actu durante cauſa metus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But let it be granted <hi>ex ſuprabundantia canſae</hi> that we were bound by the vvords of <hi>Fleta conquaeri oportet faeminam intra quadraginta dies,</hi> or that we vvere obliged by the <hi>Regiam Majeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atem</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> in theſe vvords. <hi>Si ultra unam noctem expectave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit rapta ad habendum conſilium amicorum</hi> as alſo in theſe vvords <hi>lapſu diei hoc crimen praeſcirbitur</hi> yet we have purſued the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of boath <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for ſhe not only Conſulted vvith her friends thereof but alſo made a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Complaint to the Magiſtrat, and had him thereupon Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Priſon the ſame night ſhe came to Tovvn; vvhich vvas ſo ſhort an interſpace of time as came vvithin the ſtrict confinement of a <hi>ſtatim reclamare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>About the year 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>2. there depended a cauſe of this nature between <hi>Simon Abrey</hi> and <hi>Alſoon Knight</hi> before one <hi>William Thunder</hi> official of <hi>Roger Croſs</hi> Arch-deacon of <hi>Dublin,</hi> which by appeal was brought into judgment before <hi>Robert Waren</hi> then principal official of the Metropolitical Court of the Arch-Biſhop
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34205:41"/>of <hi>Dublin,</hi> it ſeems the official of the Arch-deacon though the Marriage between the ſaid parties was contracted <hi>per vim &amp; metum</hi> decreed them to Co-habit as man and wife, and this ſentence was confirmed by the Arch-biſhops principal official for which he gave the reaſon following, <hi>viz, quia dicta Alſona quam citò potuit ab eodem Simone non effugit ſed cum eo aliquandiu permanſit,</hi> but the ſaid <hi>Alſoon</hi> upon this ſentence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, appeald from the Metropolitical Court at <hi>Dublin</hi> to the <hi>Primatiall</hi> Court at <hi>Armagh,</hi> when <hi>John</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh</hi> delegated by ſpecial Commiſſion <hi>James Leech</hi> one of the Canons of the Cathedral of <hi>Armagh</hi> to hear and determine the ſaid cauſe of appeal, where having fully heard both parties at <hi>Termon Fechan,</hi> though he found that the ſaid <hi>Alſoon</hi> had Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited with the ſaid <hi>Symon</hi> for a moneth, and her parents were conſenting thereunto; yet for as much as it appeared unto him that the Marriage was contracted <hi>per vim &amp; metum,</hi> and that ſhe made reclamation againſt the ſaid marriage and fled from the ſaid <hi>Simon,</hi> (as my Client did from the Defendent) ſo ſoon as ſhe could, he voyded and nullified the ſentence of the Arch-deacon of <hi>Dublin</hi> his Official, and of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Dublins</hi> principal Official, and decreed by his ſentence definitive as follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="text">
                              <head>IN DEI NOMINE <hi>Amen.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ditis, viſis, cognitis &amp; plenius intellectis meritis &amp; circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantijs, cauſae appellationis, &amp; ipſius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                                       <desc>•…</desc>
                                    </gap>ſae principalis, primo coram honorabili Viro Magistro</hi> Gul. Thunder <hi>officiali Domini Rogeri</hi> Croſs <hi>Archi-diaconi Dublinienſis, inter Aliciam</hi> Knight <hi>mulierem, partem actricem ex parte una, &amp; Simonem Abrey ejus
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34205:41"/>de facto maritum, partem ream ex parte altera, motae &amp; aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu pendentis indiciſae; deinde per viam appellationis, ad Curiam Melropoliticam Dublinienſem devolutae, &amp; ibidem finaliter termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natae, ac ad curiam Metropoliticam A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>machanam totius Hiberniae Primatialem denuo per appellationis Viam devolutae, &amp; nobis per Reverendiſſimum in Chriſto patrem &amp; dominum Dom. Johannem Dei &amp; Apostolicae ſedis Gratia Archiepiſcopum Armachanum, totius Hiberniae Primatem, fine Canonico terminandum commiſſae. Et quia nos viſis &amp; rimatis actis &amp; proceſſibus cauſarum hujuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di coram Magiſtro Roberto officiali Curiae Dublinienſis judice a quo introductis, &amp; coram nobis judice ad quem productis, invenimuſ<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan> per depoſitiones teſtium fide dignorum coram nobis productoruni, contra quos ſeu quorum dicta, nihil pro parte dicti Simonis erat ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectum, ſive propoſitum, &amp; alia legitima documenta animum noſtrum juſte moventia, memoratam Aliciam, ſuam intentionem, tam in appellationum, quam in ſui principalis cauſis, bene &amp; legitime fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſſe.</hi> NOS <hi>igitur Jacobus</hi> Leech <hi>Eccleſiae Armachanae Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus, partibus, &amp; cauſis antedictis Commiſſarius, per ſupraſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Reverendiſſimum Patrem, &amp; Dominum noſtrum Dom. Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Archiepiſcopum &amp; Primatem ſupradictum, ſpecialiter deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: Chriſti nomine primitus invacato, &amp; de juris Concilio perito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ad plenum deliberati, ſupradictam Aliciam bene &amp; legitime appellaſſe, ac judices ſupradictos a quibus exſtat appellatum, nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; nequiter, injuſle &amp; inique ſententiaſſe pronuntiamus, decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus &amp; declaramus; eorum<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan> ſententias infirmamus, caſsamus, irritamus, &amp; annullamus, viribuſ<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan> vacuamus, &amp; quia invenimus per depoſitiones teſtium fide dignorum, quod dicta Alicia per vim &amp; metum amicorum ſuorum compulſa, matrimonium cum dicto Simone contraxit, &amp; nunquam in eundem conſenſit, imò verius diſſenſit, quod<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan> quam citius potuit, ipſius comitivam effugit, matrimonium igitur de facto &amp; non de jure, inter dictos Aliciam &amp; Simonem contractum, quatenus de facto &amp; non de jure proceſſit, caſſamus
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34205:42"/>irritamus, &amp; annullamus, caſſum, irritum &amp; nullum dejure fuiſſe &amp; eſſe pronuntiamus decernimus &amp; declaramus, eoſdem<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan> ab invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ſeparamus, &amp; divortiamus, ac dotes &amp; donationes propter nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias, paraphernalia inter eoſdem praefata ſive donata, decernimus hinc inde fore reſtituenda, ac utri<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan> parti alibi in Domino nubendi licentiam impertientes, per hanc nostram ſententiam definitivam quam in his ſcriptis fecimus justitiâ mediante,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>By theſe two ſentences of the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Armagh</hi> his delegat, and the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Dublin</hi> his principall officiall though of a contrary tenor each to other it appears that the <hi>vim paſſa</hi> making that reclamation, and flying ſo ſoon as ſhe could did enough to avoid a marriage contracted <hi>per vim &amp; metum,</hi> they both agreed in point of law, that reclamation and flight <hi>quam cito potuit</hi> was ſufficient to that effect, for <hi>Robert Waren</hi> the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Dublins</hi> principal official being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed in point of law though miſtaken as it ſeems in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact decrees thus, <hi>quia quam cito potuit ab eodem Simone non effugit ſed cum eo aliquandiu permanſit, igitur eandem Aliciam eidem Simoni fore compellendam adharere decernimus</hi> and again <hi>James Leech</hi> delegated in the ſame cauſe by the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> being rightly informed as well in matter of fact as of law decreeth in manner following,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quia invenimus per depoſitiones testium fide dignorum quod dicta Alſona ſeu Alicia quam citius potuit dicti Simonis comitivam effugit matrimonium igitur de facto &amp; non de jure inter dictos Aliciam &amp; Simonem contractum per vim &amp; metum, quatenus de facto &amp; non de jure proceſſit caſſamus irritamus &amp; annullamus</hi> ſo that the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Dublins</hi> principal official pronounced for the marriage, becauſe he thought that the <hi>vim paſſa</hi> had not made reclamation nor fled ſo ſoon as ſhe could, and the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Armaghs</hi> delegat declared it no marriage becauſe he was aſſured by good proofs, as you have been in this cauſe that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34205:42"/>the <hi>vim paſſa</hi> did make reclamation and flye from the Defendent ſo ſoon as ſhe could <hi>quod erat probandum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> therto I have proceeded in reference to the fear and force that vvas upon her, vvhereby it appears as I humbly conceive that you ought in juſtice to pronounce ſentence againſt him, <hi>non declarando irritandum dictum matrimonium, ſed a principio irritum fuiſſe,</hi> for <hi>Panormitan</hi> holdeth in <hi>hujuſmodi matrimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um non eſt opus quod petatun reſciſſio</hi> but this is not all, vve hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly expect and deſire that the <hi>Raptor</hi> be alſo Excommunicated, for <hi>Excommunicationis paena Raptor una cum ei faventibus punitur cap. ſi quis virginem</hi> 36. <hi>q.</hi> 2. vvhich is the Conſtitution of <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the 2. <hi>in ſynodo Romana.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it ſhall be objected that the Raptor is already Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated and therefore is not to be Excommunicated againe in the ſame Cauſe for that it vvould be vain and void of effect, to this I anſvver, true it is, that the firſt Excomunication hath more effects then the ſecond can have, yet the ſecond is not vvithout its effect, for there are three effects of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation firſt a declaration of being ſeparated from God, the ſecond a ſeparation from the communion of the faithfull, the third effect is a ſtrict retention of the partie vvithout the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church, untill he be abſolved, I confeſs that it is the third effect onely that is vvrought upon one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated the ſecond time, ſo that though he ſhould be abſolved from the firſt Excommunication, yet he is to be barred the communion of the Church untill he obtain abſolution from the ſecond Excommunication, for it is true vvhat <hi>Panormitane</hi> ſaith <hi>de Iudaeis &amp; ſacracenis cap: ita quorundam</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 86.) <hi>ad primos duos effectus ſecunda exeommunicatio nihil operatur, ſed quoad tertium, ſcilicet effectnus retinendi eum extra communienem donec fuerit abſolotus, bene operatur, &amp; idem dicendum est</hi> ſaith <hi>Panormitan detertia, quarta &amp; nlteriori,</hi> vvhere it is apparent
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34205:43"/>that he may be Excommunicated and that to good effect the ſecond, third, fourth time or oftner, Againe there is a tvvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fould Excommunication the one for a Contempt, the other <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter delictum, vel injuriam alicui illatam,</hi> the Defendent being Excommunicated already for his Contempt, may be abſolved upon his appearance, ſubmiſſion and ſecurity given <hi>parere man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datis eccleſiae,</hi> but if he be once Excomunicated <hi>propter delictum</hi> he cannot obtaine abſolution <hi>quouſque parti laeſae fuerit ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,</hi> untill the partie injured receive ſatisfaction. Wherefore in regard he may be legally Excommunicated the ſecond time and that is moſt juſt he ſhould I conceive vve have good reaſon to deſire it.</p>
                  <p>Much might be ſpoken to the aggravation of this Crime vvere the ſeverity of puniſhment my chiefeſt aime, yet I ſhall make uſe at preſent but of tvvo aggravations, the one is taken from the conſideration of her being under the guard and tuition of her father, for in the booke of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> Cap. 42. it is ſaid <hi>filia patris abſcondita eſt, vigilia &amp; ſolieitudo ejus aufert ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>num, ne forte in adoleſcentia ſua adulter a efficiatur</hi> hereby it is eaſily obſerved, that that offence vvhich vvould have been noe more then fornication in a young Woman at her ovvn diſpoſall is deemed adultery in her vvho is under the tuition of her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and the reaſon is very good, for it is founded in the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude betvveen ſuch a young Woman and a Wife, for even as a marryed Woman for as much as ſhe is under the protection of her husband, and her body is her husbands, if ſhe have to do vvith any other man <hi>in congreſſu carnis</hi> doeth by the injury hereby done unto her husband become an adultereſs, ſo a vit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin vvhilſt ſhe remaines in the povver of her Father and is his as to the Cuſtody of her perſon, vvhen ſhe yeelds though through fear her body to any man, injures him, and as <hi>Gaſper Aſtete</hi> ſaith <hi>ſe puede llamar adultera</hi> may be called an adultereſs
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34205:43"/>as ſhe is termed <hi>Ecleſiaſticus</hi> the 42 whence it is inferred by the Caſuiſts, that, when ſhe vvho is under the povver of her Father looſeth her Virginity even in the Caſe of Rape; it is ſuch a circumſtance as muſt neceſſarily be mentioned in her Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for that it changeth <hi>ſpeciem peccati,</hi> and is a <hi>ſin</hi> of inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice as vvell as of Luxurie, vvhereas a Virgin not being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the povver, of a Father but at her own diſpoſe, if ſhe looſe her Maiden-head, although it be a ſin of Luxury, the Doctors ſay it is no ſin of injuſtice, noris it an offence to any other for ſo much as ſhe is <hi>domina ſui Corporis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other aggravation is ſo well expres'd in the words of the Poet <hi>Catullus</hi> that the recital of them in their Original, will be ſufficient without proſtitution to vulgar underſtandings.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t flos in ſeptis ſecretus naſcitur herbis</l>
                     <l>Ignotus pecori, nullo ſucciſſus aratro,</l>
                     <l>Quem mulcent aurae, format ſol, educat imler,</l>
                     <l>Multi illum pueri, multae optavère puellae,</l>
                     <l>Idem cum tenui captus defloruit ungue,</l>
                     <l>Nulli illum pueri, nullae optavere puellae:</l>
                     <l>Sic virgo cum intacta manet, dum chara ſuis,</l>
                     <l>Cum castum amiſit, polluta Corpore, florem,</l>
                     <l>Nec pueris haec chara manet nec chara puellis.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>There remains yet in arrear one branch of the Cauſe his jactitation of Marriage which in the opinion of <hi>Grotius Deſerues</hi> as great a penalty as his other offence for in his annotations on the 22 <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> he ſaith <hi>diffamater par habetur inferenti vim virgini,</hi> andn owonder for the Rabins reckon Calumniators amongſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> that is to ſay amongſt thoſe who are not to ſee God in glory (<hi>vid animadver: in Pirk</hi> p. 253)</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:34205:44"/>
                  <p>This matter of diffamation is ſo clearly proved againſt him, and the Law is ſo evident in daily practize as to that point, that ſhall not ſo much abuſe your patience and leaſure, as to ſpend time and words in rendring it more evident, nor ſhall I deſire more of your juſtice therein at preſent, then to pronounce him guilty of an unjuſt and temerary jactitation of Marriage with the actrix, to impoſe on him perpetual ſilence in that behalf, and laſtly to Condemn him in all our expences, all which we hope and humbly deſire that you will immediatly pronounce, for that we are confident the Caſe is ſo Cleer that it need not lye longer in the ballance of deliberation, and that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I have ſaid in this debate may be interpreted no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="notification">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:34205:44"/>
                  <head>Short Advertiſements given to the ſaid Court and Auditory after ſentence pronounced, delivered in a ſpeech by <hi>Dudley Loftus</hi> Doctor of the Laws &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>MY promiſe hath made me deptor to the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this aſſembly for an advertiſment which I thought to have given then in the ſeries of my former diſcourſe, which through haſt I then omitted, if therefore I may preſume on your favour and licence, I ſhall take advantage of ſo many witneſſes of good note as are here preſent, to make a reflection in a word or two, on the Plaintiffs caſe, wherein If I ſhall ſay any thing not agreeable to your opinion, I ſhall in all the flexures of humility ſubmit to your correction and the regulation of your better judgment, me thinks I heare moſt perſons declare the ſatisfaction they have received in your moſt righteous judgment, yet ſome ſeem to be of opinion that the ſplendour of your juſtice ſhines upon the Lady no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then as the Sun profuſely ſheds its beams on blaſted bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms which receive no benefit thereby, and others think that chaſtity without Virginity is but as a Garland of Flowers that hath loſt its ſent and colour; for my part I have already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared my opinion, that untouch't Virginity is the moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Jewel of the femall ſex, and I do agree with <hi>Arioſto</hi> who ſaith.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:34205:45"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Non nobilita ne gran fortuna baſta,</l>
                     <l>Se per nome e per opere non e caſta.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And I confeſs that it was a great misfortune that the bud of her Virginity was pul'd from the ſtalke before it could ſpread or ſhew it ſelf in marriage, and that ſhe cannot receive an aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent exchange in ſatisfaction of that which ſhe hath loſt; yet I dare affirm that this loſs hath not brought her into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace with prudent men, nor doth her honour thereby go into diminution, for ſhe hath no more ſtained her reputation then ſhe hath ſtung her conſcience by enduring that which ſhe could not avoid, inſomuch that I dare appeal to the ſtricteſt tribunal on earth for judgment, whether ſhe hath received ſo much as <hi>faniae vulnuſculum</hi> by the force offered unto her; nay I am of opinion that ſome unſucceſsfull conteſts are to be preferred before ſome Victories for which reaſon <hi>Tornay</hi> in France bears a Badge of Reputation to this day for that <hi>Caeſar</hi> confeſſeth in his Comentaries that he found a more valourous reſiſtance there then elſewhere, I am confident the reaſon may be urged much more to the advantage of the perſons who made the reſiſtance then the place where it was made, and if ſo, I reſt aſſured my Client hath more reaſon to glory on the Theatre of a publike appearance then to ſhrink into the ſhade of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, or to hide her ſelf in the dark corners of a baſhfull retirement, for let us conſider her firſt of all <hi>ratione metus concuſſi,</hi> and then <hi>ratione vis illatae,</hi> as to the firſt it is confeſt that a married woman if ſhe ſhould yield to an adulterous act by reaſon of fear, (though it were ſo great as might be incident to a valiant man) ſhe would in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Caſuiſts be held guilty of adultery, <hi>quia metu mortis non licet contra legem agere quae eſt juris naturae, eo quod
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34205:45"/>intrinſicam habet malitiam,</hi> for not to preſerve the fidelity of Wedlock is againſt the law of nature and in it ſelf in trinſical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evill, and therefore not excuſable upon any conſideration of fear though never ſo great: But a Virgin, if ſhe through fear conſent (which my Client did not.) to a conſtupration, ſhe is not guilty of the formall evill thereof, for <hi>non cenſetur Cooperatio in malo niſi ubi res eſt intrinſice mala non pendens a voluntate Concurrentis</hi> ſaith <hi>Candidus de Confeſſione ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali Artic.</hi> 23. <hi>Dubio.</hi> 12, but <hi>malitia ſtupri</hi> doth ſo depend on the will of the woman that <hi>illa concurrente tollatur,</hi> but <hi>illa renitente ponatur,</hi> the difference of the two caſes conſiſts in this, that the circumſtance of the two caſes conſiſts in this, that the circumſtance of adultery doth not depend <hi>ex voluntate faeminae</hi> as that of Conſtupration doth, ſo that if my Client had yielded through fear, ſhe had not been guilty of the evil of Conſtupration, (though the ſtricter Caſuiſts would perhaps extend it <hi>ad malitiam fornicationis</hi>) but the caſe is otherwiſe with my Client for fear did not prevaile with her, ſhe was compelled by force,</p>
                  <p>And ye know that force and imbecillity are the great diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhers of ſin inſomuch that not to commit a ſin through im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillity makes one guilty of ſin, whereas to be concern'd in ſin through imbecillity excuſeth from ſin, wherefore ſaith a famous Doctor of the Lawes <hi>Johannes de Moutholon in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance</hi> of the firſt poſition, <hi>qui ſola virium imbecillitate deſinit peccare reus peccati eſt, quia ream mentem habet, vide Cap ſi cni etiam de paenitentia diſt.</hi> 1. and in proof of the later poſition viz, that to be concern'd in ſin through imbecillity excuſeth from guilt, I ſhall produce a teſtimony from the very fountain of the law, for <hi>Azo</hi> who is termed <hi>fons legum</hi> ſaith in concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with <hi>Baldus, tolle voluntatem de medio &amp; omnis act us erit indifferens,</hi> and therefore <hi>Gabriel Biel</hi> expreſſeth himſelf thus, <hi>in voluntariis ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> vituperamur neque landamur,</hi> which agreeth
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34205:46"/>with this ſaying of St. <hi>Auſtin, violentia non violatur pudicitiae faeminae, quia violenter Compreſſa, Carne non utitur, ſed ſine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſu toleratur quod alius operatur,</hi> that father is yet more clear in this point when ſpaking of a married man who forced a modeſt woman, he ſaith <hi>duo in adulterio fuerunt unus commiſit,</hi> the reaſon hereof may be perfectly rendred in the obſervation of <hi>Nicholaus de Orbello,</hi> viz, that as the underſtanding being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Dominion of anger is nor <hi>ſui juris,</hi> ſo <hi>timentes vel vi oppreſſi non habent voluntatis plenditudinem</hi> nay rather <hi>velle non dicitur qui metus cauſa vult vel vi oppreſſus ſuccumbit,</hi> to this you may add the words of <hi>Baldus Metus eſt participatio duarum qualitatum ſcilicet voluntatis &amp; noluntatis, cujus effectus declinat ad velle, &amp; affect us inclinat ad nolle. de his quae vi metuſue cauſa fiunt, Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 5. and <hi>Accurſius</hi> declares that <hi>voluntas meticulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa est tac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ta quaedam contradictio, &amp; mrgis accedit diſſenſui quam conſenſui.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Perhaps the foregoing arguments did not ſlide ſo ſmoothly into the apprehenſion of the unlearned as I could wiſh, for they were taken out of the knotty timber of School divinity, which for the moſt part rejecteth the plain, yet I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make my ſelf more inteligible to them in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains.</p>
                  <p>I know that many ingenious perſons do oftentimes inſinuat falſe opinions into the minds of the ignorant and do invade the perſwaſions of leſs diſcerning perſons by a licentious raylle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie which may be termed a blamable liberty of practizing witt too freely, and that it is an eaſie matter for ſuch ignorant perſons to be deluded thereby, who having no further recourſe then to their own imaginations will not remit ſuch matters to the examination of reaſon.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is that this Ladies condition hath been drawn into debate, and though ſome perſons and they of honour and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34205:46"/>judgment, hold it for as evident a truth, as that the three angles of a triangle are equall to two right angles, that ſhe is no whit prejudiced by her late misfortune, yet others ſeem to be of opinion, that ſhe is thereby brought under the ſuſpition if not preſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mption of worſe diſpoſitions, and a greater facility of temptation, and that therefore ſhe is notably damnified in her reputation, which opinion is promoted with too much temerity by ſome of like mind with the Jeſuiſts, who as the Franciſcans ſay by a dexterous manner of depreſſing other religious orders, ſeek to procure grandeur to themſelves, but do not conſider that the beſt way to defend their own repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, is to be carefull of the credit of others, for my part I ſhall not preciſely determine the matter to the tenet of either of thoſe parties, for we are not now in the blazon, are tricking a coat in Heraldry, where ſo ſmall a thing as a colour of one hair makes a coat another thing, as in <hi>Erminites;</hi> but I think that things of this nature are like to the time which the rules of religion appoint for the recital of howers, which as the Caſuiſts teach <hi>habet aliquid latitudinis,</hi> the later opinion ſeems to me too ſevere &amp; grounded upon a temerary ſurmiſe, not to be warranted by any principle of piety or rule of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and though the firſt opinion may be in courtſhip admitted as a favourable miſtake, for the Ladies advantage; yet I think it beſt to temper the extremity of theſe two opinions in a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle way though <hi>Sub conditione crucis,</hi> my opinion therefore is that though ſhe is not altogether as ſhe was before to every fancy, yet is ſhe not really or conſiderably the worſe in the opinion of the moſt judicious and if there be any difference between the ſtate of her untoucht virginity, and her new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmd chaſtitie of mind, as to valuation it is almoſt like that of the ſtarrs in the firmament whoſe different magnitudes are not
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34205:47"/>perceptible to the moſt clear ſeeing eye, ſo that I preſume that a raviſht innocent, and an untoucht Virgin may ſeem to ſhine with equal ſplendor in their reſpective! Orbs, and that this chaſt Lady may be reſembled to the pure mettall of the Crown pieces of the ſometime Lords Juſtices of this Kingdom, which though their ſtamp and impreſſion ſhould be altered, or loſt, would notwithſtanding carry no leſs int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inſick value in the ſame weight; the Duke of <hi>Sommerſet</hi> ſaid that all his actings were blameleſs in the eye of juſtice, ſo I may ſay that all her ſufferings in the time of her abduction were as innocent in the eye of honour, nay that the Heroick acts performed by her in the defence of her chaſtitie do exceed a volumn of their vertues who have preſerved the integrity of their bodies: <hi>quid enim prodeſt pudicitia corporis animo conſtuprato</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> in <hi>Jeremiam lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>Again it is a thing agreeable to the ingenuity of all worthy perſons to obſerve that law which they impoſe upon others, and therefore <hi>l. ff. de pact is</hi> it is ſaid <hi>nihil tam humanae fidei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaneum eſt quam ea quae placuerunt ſervari,</hi> give me leave therefore in a modeſt fredome to aske the moſt vertuous Lady amongſt you what ſhe could have thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t criminal in her ſelf to have been forced as that Lady was, I hope enough hath been ſpoken to determine your judgment in this affair ſo farr at leaſt as to clear her reputation, and I know that to inſiſt too much on the proof of ſo clear a truth would cruſh your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as flat as a <hi>(B)</hi> after a cliff, I ſhall therefore immediatly coaſt upon a concluſion and therein deſire you rather to lament her late ſufferings with tenderneſs of heart then judge her preſent condition with ſeverity of cenſure, let no man diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge upon her innocency the miſapprehenſions of his wild fancy or untamed wit, let no man make her Rape farther mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34205:47"/>of diſcourſe, but rather let that misfortune be hidden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the vail of perpetual forgetfulneſs, let the Garland of chaſtity remain unwithered on her brow let her flowriſh in an honourable reputation whilſt the Defendant deſerves to have his goods confiſcate and his Memory baniſhed out of the world: and let her vertuous mind enjoy the quiet of a Serene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, whilſt his black Soul is left during Divine pleaſure to the diſmal horrour of midnight dreams, to the terrors of the law, and the dreadfull apprehenſions of the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
